<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The worthye booke of old age othervvyse entituled the elder Cato contayning a learned defence and praise of age, and aged men: writen in latine by that father of eloquence Marcus Tullius Cicero, and now englished. VVherunto is annexed a recitall of diuerse men that liued long. With a declaracion of sundrye soortes of yeares, and the diuersitie betwene the yeres in the old time, and our yeares nowe adayes. Anno. 1569</title>
            <title>Cato maior de senectute. English</title>
            <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1569</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857288</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857288</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 316:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The worthye booke of old age othervvyse entituled the elder Cato contayning a learned defence and praise of age, and aged men: writen in latine by that father of eloquence Marcus Tullius Cicero, and now englished. VVherunto is annexed a recitall of diuerse men that liued long. With a declaracion of sundrye soortes of yeares, and the diuersitie betwene the yeres in the old time, and our yeares nowe adayes. Anno. 1569</title>
                  <title>Cato maior de senectute. English</title>
                  <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius.</author>
                  <author>Newton, Thomas, 1542?-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64, [7] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1569]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Cato Major de senectute.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Thomas Nevvton.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Old age --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:1"/>
            <p>THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye Booke of Old age othervvyſe entituled the elder Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, contayning a learned defence and praiſe of Age, and Aged men: writen in latine by that father of eloquence <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Tullius Cicero,</hi> and now engliſhed.</p>
            <p>VVherunto is annexed a Recitall of diuerſe men that liued long.</p>
            <p>With a declaracion of ſundrye ſoortes of yeares, and the diuerſitie betwene the yeres in the old time, and our yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes.</p>
            <p>Anno, 1569</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Marſhe.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right high and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lord, VVillyam Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, of the noble order of the Garter Knyghte, Lorde S. Iohn, Earle of Wylſhyre, Marques of Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and Lord Treaſurour of Englande.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as (ryght Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) I hadde fyniſhed this my rude tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Marcus Tullius Cicero his Booke of old age, begonne and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by me this laſt yere hauing a quiet time of vacation among my frendes in Cheſshyre, therby to exclude and avoyde that lothſome and horrible Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Idleneſſe, whych holye Ambroſe apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye calleth the Pillowe or Cuſsyon of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, I called my wittes to counſayle and ſtudyed in my mind to whom my ſymple trauayle therein employed might beſte bee dedicated. Amonge all others, I could find none, vnto whome the whole proceſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:22986:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>the matter, and the excellencye of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſeemed better to agre, then to your Lordſhippe. Vſing therefore the graue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the famous Philoſopher and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Ethnike (for ſo doubtethe not Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus to cal him) Seneca, vvho vvilleth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that meaneth to beſtovve any gift or preſent vpon anye maner of perſon, not onelye to haue a diligent eye and reſpecte, that his ſayd gift be ſuch, as to his eſtate and degree is meete and agreeable, but alſo ſuch as to the dignitie and calling of the receauer is apt and conuenable: I humblye offer this litle Treatyſe of Olde age vnto youre ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as vnto him, in vvho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Olde age to the great reioycing of al your vvelvvillers moſt triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phantly flouriſheth: truſting, yea rather not doubting, but that your L. vvil as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourablye accepte it, as the noble king Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxerxes (ſurnamed Memor) did a Pomegra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate vvhiche one of his ſubiectes preſented him vvithal or as at an other time, hee did a lytle fayre riuer vvater, vvhyche a poore Perſian Peazaunte (ſeeinge manye people
<pb facs="tcp:22986:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>thicke and threefolde to brynge revvardes to the kinge, and he hauinge nothinge, yet loth to come behinde vvith the ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his poore loyal hearte tovvarde his Soueraigne) offerred vnto him in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovvneſſe of his tvvo handes: or (to take an example neerer home, and of a Prynce of later dayes) as the politique and prudent Loys the eleuenthe of that name kinge of Fraunce, did a Radiſhe roote, preſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym by the handes of his poore vaſſall and Subiecte Conon the Burgonion. And becauſe beſyde a fruictful and learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of age, there be herein alſo enterla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced manye proper concluſions and feactes contryued in the prayſe and comendacion of Huſbandry, vvherin not onelye meane gentlemen and honourable Senatours, but alſo mighty monarches and puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in old time toke great delight and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, together with a chronologie of diuers heroical and vvorthy enterpriſes, atchieued partly by martial provveſſe, partly by vviſe do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and pollicy: theſe al ſemed moſt fit to be
<pb facs="tcp:22986:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>dedicated vnto youre excellencye, vvho is and of longe time hath bene the principall huſband of this famous Realme vnder our royall and ſoueraigne Princeſſe, and others her Graces noble Predeceſſours: vvho alſo moſt honourablye and faithfully haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her highnes and theym in their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and vvaightye affayres booth at home and in other forraine Realmes in great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure and eſtimation. VVhom God hath bleſſed vvith ſo proſperous a race of longe lyfe, to ſee the Children of your Childrens Children: ympes for their tovvardnes not lyke to degenerate from the vertue of their great Graundfather, neyther to forſake the ſteppes of their noble Graundfather. Here wil I vvade no farder, to ſpeake any thing, of the vertuous geftes incorporate in your noble breaſt, partly becauſe it mighte pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raduenture ſeeme to ſmel of that vglie vice, vvhiche I dooe and euer haue deteſted, (I meane Adulation) and partly becauſe they ſufficiently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend themſelues to the eye of the vvorld, in ſo much that in reſpect of
<pb facs="tcp:22986:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, my vvordes might be but as it vvere a candle lighted at high noone to helpe the ſhyning of the bright Sunne at midſomer. VVherfore in receyuing this vvorthy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoure and his ſmal traine, vvhom in this Dialogue he entroduceth reaſoning and tal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king one vvith an other of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities and diſcommodities of old age into youre patrocinie and protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (vvhoſe ſugred ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and pregnau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtyle, fraughted vvith a legion of vvitty perſvvaſions and eloquet argumentes, Penned by that incomparable Phenix of al eloquence among al that euer vvrate either before or ſince his dayes, I for lack of knovvledge haue racked from gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Elegancie, and oute of Romayne govvnes more boldly I feare then vvyſelye chaunged into Englyſ he Liuerayes) you ſhal acquire and purchaſe great praiſe and glorie. Aſſuring your ſelf, that in defending and ſhrovvdinge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the poyſoned and ſlaunderous infamyes of ſerpentine Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophantes, and the cancard aſſaultes of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious tongues, vvhiche ſeede on no other
<pb facs="tcp:22986:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>repaſt but ſpightful diſdaine and helliſhe rancoure, your L. ſhal do a thing (vnleſſe I be much deceyued) greatly ſounding to the generoſitie of youre noble hart and highe eſtate. For vvhat greater praiſe can there be then to be a patrone of vertue, and of them that are vertuous? Againe, vvherin is the honoure of the Honourable ſoe much ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, dymmed and Eclipſed, as in bolſte ring vice, and ſupporting the vvicked? Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept therfore (Right noble Lord this poore earneſt penye of my vnfayned good vvil into your tuition, vvherby I ſhal be any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and encouraged hereafter perhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes to attempte ſome vvaightier matter.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon, humblye and vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmittinge my ſelfe and al that I can do, to your Cenſure and commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, I ſurceaſſe anye longer to trouble you. Beſeching God the Authoure and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of al good thinges, ſo to infuſe his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious giftes into you, that after the Epilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue and laſt Pageaunt of this mortal and tranſitorye lyfe (VVherin youre L. vvith
<pb facs="tcp:22986:5"/>much vvorſhippe, more honour, and moſt authorytie theſe lxxxxvi. yeres hath ben a worthye and honourable Actor) you may be tranflated into the ioyes celeſtial, and be made partaker of his glorious kingdome Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Frome Butleye <date>the ſeuenth of Marche. 1569.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your L. moſt humble Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure Thomas Nevvton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I did not gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der truſte more to thy frendly curteſie thenne to myne owne ſkill and iudgement, I would not with hazard of my fame haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſed the diuulgacion of this my ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple trauaile to the gazinge view of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye ſcrupulous and criticall behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But becauſe it pleaſed ſome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire me (who notwithſtanding had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to comaunde me, to take this ſmall charge in hand. I am bold vpon their encouragemente and likinge to conceyue ſemblable hope of thy frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fauourable acceptaunce. Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it long it was, ere I would willinglye relent to their requeſtes, pleadinge in excuſe of my vnablenes, and aledging
<pb facs="tcp:22986:6"/>the incomparable ſublymity and ſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye eloquence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Authoure, wherby my Conſcience vpbrayded me of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, in that, I hauing but a ſmal ſclender veſſel would aduenture into any ſuche ſea. Furthermore I was not ignoraunte howe this ſame was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated about xxx yeares agone: but of al doubtes, this was the leaſte, for as much as that tranſlation beareth but the countenaunce of one, being none in dede to any purpoſe, being taken of the learned for noone at all, ſithens neuer a page almoſt is anſwerable to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine textè, I wil not ſay, ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. Take therfore wel in worth my good, wil and aford me gentle report for my laboure which is the ſole guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that I do expect at thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, and thinke not that the tranſlatours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkilfulnes
<pb facs="tcp:22986:7"/>doth any thing derogate from the Authours worthynes, waigh my intente in the Balance of frende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe and indifferencye, who to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile the wante of power, am ſtored wïth as muche good wil as the beſt to pleaſure the.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Farrwell. <hi>T. Newton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:7"/>
            <head>The Preſace of the Authour <hi>vnto Titus pomponius Atticus.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>O Tytus, if I eaſe thee of that paine,</l>
                  <l>And heauie charg vvhich doth the ſore annoy,</l>
                  <l>And makes thine hart ful penſiue to remain,</l>
                  <l>Shal I herein my laboure vvell employe?</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>For in ſpeaking vnto the (friend Atticus) I maye vſe the ſame verſes and woordes, whiche that auncient and worthie Potte, more fully fraughted vvith honeſtye, and faithful dealing, than vvith vvorldly pelfe and rycheſſe, vſeth, in coumforting the no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble Flaminius: albeit I am vvell aſſured, that thou art not ſo diſquieted night and day, vvith penſiuenes, care, and ſorovve, as Flaminius vvas: for I knovve thy paei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente ſufferaunce of all chaunces and brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Fortune, and the vvell ſtayed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy mynde. And I do ryghte vvell vnderſtande hovve that thou haſte broughte hoome vvythe thee frome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, not onelye thy Surrename, to bee
<pb facs="tcp:22986:8"/>called Atticus, but alſo gentle behauioure, courteſie, and prudence. Yet canne I not othervvyſe thynke, but that, novve and then aſvvel as I, thou arte ſore vexed and troubled in minde, for the tyrannous oppreſſions and greuous enormities novv in our common vvealthe perpetrated and comitted. The conſolation vvherof is ſo great, that it can not in this litle booke be fully declared, and therfore I vvil defer it, vntill an other time more conuenient. At this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time, I thought it beſt to vvrit ſom litle Treatiſe vnto the, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Old age: becauſe I vvould faine haue both thee and my ſelfe, to be eaſed of this heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, which is commune and indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to me aſvvell as to thee, (I meane Olde age,) vvhich novve already is either come vpon vs, or els ere it be longe, (we maye be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) will catche holde on vs. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I know well that thou doeſt and wilt take the ſame modeſtlye, and as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a wiſe man to do, pacientlye, euen as thou arte in all other thynges accuſtomed.</p>
            <p>But vvhenne as I purpoſed vvythe my ſelfe to vvrite ſomevvhat in prayſe and commendacion of Olde age, I deemed and
<pb facs="tcp:22986:8"/>iudged the moſt vvorthy, vnto vvhom my laboure and ſtudie in this behalfe myght be dedicated, vvhiche boothe of vs, mighte ioyntlie and commonly vſe for our coum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte and contentacion. As for my part, I promiſe thee, I toke ſuch ſinguler pleaſure and delectacion in the compilinge of this Booke, that it did not onelye vtterlie take avvaie al the encombraunces and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of mine Olde age from mee: but rather made the ſame vnto me pleaſaunt, ioyfull, and delectable. Therefore Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie canne neuer be ſufficientlye praiſed, ſo muche as the vvorthineſſe and dignitie thereof requireth: vvhoſe preceptes and rules vvho ſo euer obayeth, maye paſſe the vvhole time of his age, and runne the full race of this life, vvithoute anye yrkeſome griefe or trouble. VVhat other vtilities and commodities it bringeth, I haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in manye other of my Bookes at large declared and meane hereafter manie times and often therof to make ample diſcourſe and mencion. But this Booke of Old age, I haue ſent vnto thee: vvherein the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and ſuperioritie of the diſputacion is not geeuen to olde Tithonus as Ariſto
<pb facs="tcp:22986:9"/>Chius did in his Booke, leaſt in ſuche a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fable the vvhole diſcourſe ſhould bee the leſſe eſteemed among the Readers: but I attribute the chyefe dignytie of it vnto the Old grayheaded ſage Marcus Cato, to thende the Treatiſe ſhoulde haue moore eſtimation credite and authoritie. And I introduce as ſpeakers, Laelius and Scipio, frankly and familierlie talking vvith him, and muche meruailinge to ſee him, ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlie and eaſelie to tolerate his old age, and vvhat aunſvveares hee made to theim again. VVhom if thou thinke more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlye heare to diſpute, then in his ovvne vvoorkes he vvas accuſtomed, impute the cauſe to his ſkilfulnes in the Greeke ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, vvhereof it is vvell knovven that in his Olde age he vvas very ſtudious. But to vvhat purpoſe ſhould vve make any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preamble? for al that vve haue to ſay concerning Olde age, the talke and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion of Cato himſelfe ſhall manifeſtlye declare.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22986:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Speakers names.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Publius Scipio.</item>
                  <item>Caius Laelius.</item>
                  <item>Marcus Cato.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scipio.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F tentymes boothe I and my freinde <hi>Caius Laelius</hi> alſo, are wont greatly to haue in an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miracion &amp; to meruayle at the excellent and abſolute wiſedome O <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> which thou vſeſt in all other matters and exploites what ſo euer thou takeſt in hand: but namely and ſpecially, bicauſe we neuer yet perceiued thyne old age to be burthenous and gréeuous vnto thée, whiche to the moſt parte of old men is ſo odious and vnwelcome, that they wil ſay they carie aboute with theym a burthen heautour then the great flaming Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Aetna.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22986:10"/>
                  <hi>Cato.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>A verie ſlight and eaſie matter it is (deare frends <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Laelius</hi>) which you do ſéeme ſo muche to muſe and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile at: for they that haue no power, pith of witte helpe, waye nor vertue in them ſelues, to conducte and bring theym to a good and bleſſed life, vnto ſuche as theſe bée, all their age is comberſome and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſaunt. But vnto ſuch, as leade their lyues vertuouſlye, meaſurynge all their actions by the ſquyre of reaſon, and haue their minds with al good giftes of grace beautified and garniſhed, ther is nothing thought ne déemed euil, that commeth by neceſſitie of nature. Of the which ſorte, Olde age is principally to be conſidered, vnto which all men wiſhe to arriue, and yet when they haue their deſire, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it, as painfull, ſicklie, vnpleaſaunte and tedious, ſuche is the braineleſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie, fooliſhe ſottage and peruerſe ouerth wartnes of waywarde people.</p>
               <p>They ſaye, it crepeth and ſtealeth vppon them, faſter and ſoner then they thought
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22986:10"/>it woulde. Fyrſt, who cauſeth theym to ymagine and thinke ſuch a falſe and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh vntruth? for why ſhould they thinke that after their youthe and adoleſcencie, Old age créepeth faſter vpon theym, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their adoleſcencie and youthe doth after childhode? Seing therfore they do not repine nor complaine any whitte, after that they haue ben children, to grow to be tall Striplinges and luſtie younge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, why ſhoulde they be aggreued or thinke theym ſelues diſcontented, after they haue bene Striplinges and younge men, to bée Old and aged? Againe, if they might reach to the age of eight hundreth yeres, what greater pleaſure and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie is therein, or wherein ſhoulde they thinke it to be leſſe trouble ſome, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, then it is when they bee of thage of foure ſcore yeares? for the age that is once paſſed &amp; gone, be it neuer ſo longe, can with no maner of pleaſure or delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, comfort, recreat, nor mytigate, the old age that is in ſuch fonde perſons. And
<pb facs="tcp:22986:11"/>therefore if you bée wonte to wonder at me, and to haue my wiſedome in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (which I would to god were cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to your good opinion concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of mee, and alſo anſwerable to my Surname) we are in this onelye poincte wyſe, becauſe we folow nature as a god, and takinge her as a ſure and infallible guide, direct and leauel al our actions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her preſcript lawes and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces. Of whom, when all the other partes of age are well deſcribed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted, it is not like to be true, that the laſt acte of al ſhold be negligently plaied &amp; as it wer of an vnſkilful and dreaming Poete, loyteringly handeled. But in age there muſt néedes bee ſome extreme and laſt end, bending downe, drowping, and declyning from the luſtines and nymble actiuitie that was in flouriſhing youth, as it hapeneth &amp; is plainly to be ſéene in the bearies of trées and other fruicts of the earth, when they be com to their due ripenes &amp; natural maturitie: which euery
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22986:11"/>wiſe man wil paciently &amp; willingly tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. For what other thing is ment, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temerarious &amp; proud attempt of the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, warring &amp; obſtinately fighting with the gods, but to reſiſt &amp; go againſt nature?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Laelius.</speaker>
               <p>But you ſhal do a ſinguler great pleaſure vnto vs both (for I dare vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take for <hi>Scipio</hi> &amp; ſpeake for him in thys poinct aſwell as for my ſelfe) to geue vs ſome fruictfull premonition wherby we may aforehand be inſtructed and alſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (becauſe bothe deſire &amp; hope to lyue til we be old men) by what meanes wée may moſt eaſelie ſuffer &amp; beare out oure old croked age, when it cometh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cato.</speaker>
               <p>I wil <hi>(Laelie)</hi> fulfil your requeſt &amp; willingly rele<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your peticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly if I ſhal therby do ſuch pleaſure vnto both of you, as you ſay I ſhal.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scip.</speaker>
               <p>Right glad wold we be, if it might pleaſe you, &amp; be not to much paines &amp; trouble for you O <hi>Cato,</hi> ſithe you haue as it were runne a great race, and gone a longe iourneye, (which path alſo we muſt tread) to heare
<pb facs="tcp:22986:12"/>and vnderſtand what kynd of thing that is, whereunto you are alreadie arryued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cato.</speaker>
               <p>I will doe herein O <hi>Laelie</hi> what I am able: for I haue oftentimes bene in companye amonge my equalles and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myliers (for, like with like, accordinge to the old prouerbe, wil kepe company and beſt agre together) who haue greatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed the diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie of their old yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; thought them ſelues in an ill caſe by reaſon of their age, and namely <hi>Caius Salinator</hi> and <hi>Spurius Albinus,</hi> men that haue ben Conſuls, &amp; in maner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame age y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I my ſelfe am, were wont greatly to murmure and repyne, ſorowinge and lamentinge for their old age: not onelye becauſe they thoughte theym ſelues to lacke pleaſures and laſciuious paſtimes, and to be vtterlye bereft &amp; debarred from al ioyes and ſolaces, without whom they accompted their life to bee as no life, but alſo becauſe they were contemned and deſpyſed of thoſe, of whome they were wonte to be honoured, and reuerenced.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22986:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>But in my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they blamed not that, whiche was blame worthye. For if the cauſe and blame therof, wer to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to old age, then ſhoulde the ſame diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodities, coraſies and gréeuaunces happen vnto me and al other old men, of whom I haue knowen a great maignie, that haue liued in their olde age without any whyning, complaint, or diſcontenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: who were well pleaſed to be vngi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, looſed and deliuered out of the yoke of their ſenſuall luſtes and voluptuous appetites, who alſo were neuer deſpyſed of their friends and acquaintaunce. But the blame &amp; fault of al this mutteringe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleyning is in the ouerth wartenes of mens wayward maners and not in age. For diſcrete, ſober, and temperate olde men, being neither ill to pleaſe, froward nor churliſhe, do liue in their old age to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably and quietly ynough, both to them ſelues and al others. But vnbrideled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie, and blunt vncurteſie, is to al age vnpleaſaunt, tedious &amp; yrkſome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Laelius.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22986:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>It is euen ſo, as you ſay <hi>Cato,</hi> but there wil ſome peraduenture ſaye vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your olde age, ſéemeth to you tolerable ynough, becauſe of your great wealthe, rycheſſe and dignitie, but ther be a great numbre of others, whiche can not haue ſuch ample poſſeſſions nor ſuch extra or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie helpes to alleuiate and condul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſperitie and vnpleaſauntenes of their decrepite age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cato.</speaker>
               <p>In déede <hi>Laelie</hi> that whereof you haue nowe talked is ſomewhat, but all thinges do not reſt nor conſiſt in them: wherunto agréeth the quick and nipping ſentence of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> vnto whome, when as a certain raſcal peaſaunt of the Iſle of <hi>Scriphos</hi> tauntingly &amp; ſpightfully ſaid, that he had not gotten ſo great fame and renowne of hym ſelfe, but rather through the noble and glorious celebri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his flouriſhinge countrie: Thou ſayeſt truthe (ſaid he) for if I had bene a <hi>Scriphian</hi> berne, I ſhould neuer haue ben enuobled nor my name by ſo manye tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22986:13"/>victories blaſed abroad &amp; eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized, neither if thou were an <hi>Athenian</hi> borne, thou ſhouldeſt neuer aſpire to any honorable dignity. In like maner may it be ſaid of oldage, for in extreme penurie, ſcarcitie &amp; indigence it can not be eaſilye abyden, born, &amp; tolerated, no not of a wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: neither it cannot be but cumbreſome &amp; greuous to him that is a foole, although he haue neuer ſo great plenty, &amp; abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of althings. The very méeteſt weapons &amp; fitteſt inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for old age (O <hi>Scipio</hi> &amp; <hi>Laelie</hi>) are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfect knowledge &amp; the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue exerciſes of vertue, whiche when it hath bene practiſed all the time of mans age, which hath liued a long time, dothe bring &amp; yeld at length meruelous fruict &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity, not only becauſe it neuer ſhrin keth nor ſtarteth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, nor yet forſaketh vs, no not in the verie laſt poinct of age (which truly is an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thing) but alſo becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our former life which we haue led vertuouſlye, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of many good &amp; pitiful dedes before tyme
<pb facs="tcp:22986:14"/>and of ſundrye noble actes valiantlye at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieued is verie pleaſaunt, comfortable, and delectable vnto vs. Certes, I when I was a yong ſtripling did ſo loue <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Maximus,</hi> (the ſame was he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the Citie of <hi>Tarentine</hi>) beynge then an old man, as though he had bene myne equall and of like age as I was.</p>
               <p>For in that noble and prudent man, ther was to bee ſéene a kinde of ſeueritie and magnificence mingled &amp; powdred with clemencie and a mercifull generoſitie.</p>
               <p>His old age neuer altered nor chaunged his wonted maners, albeit when I firſt began to honoure and reuerence him, for the vertuous magnanymitie whiche I eſpied to raigne in him, he was not very old, but yet he was wel ſtriken in yeres. For I was borne one yeare after he had bene the firſte time Conſull, and in his fourthe Couſulate, I being a yong man, was a Souldioure vnder hym in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition to <hi>Capua,</hi> the fift yere after that, I was made Treaſurour and general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22986:14"/>at <hi>Tarentine,</hi> then was I created <hi>Aedilis,</hi> and within foure yeres after, I was elected <hi>Praetor,</hi> whych office I bare and executed when <hi>Tuditanus</hi> and <hi>Cethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> were Conſuls. At that time he being a verie aged man, in publique audience counſailed the Senate &amp; people of Rome to reuiue the Lawe called <hi>Lex Cincia,</hi> &amp; to haue it to ſtand in effect &amp; to be duelie executed. And being a man farre growen in yeres, he warred in the quarrel of hys Countrie, and to repulſe forraine hoſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, was choſen Chieuetaine and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the warres, wherin he ſo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye acquited himſelfe with proweſſes and pollicie, and was ſo couragious and laborious, as though he had ben a luſtie yonge Gallaunt in his floriſhing &amp; freſh yeres, yea &amp; with his lingering pacience &amp; procraſtinacion, repreſſed and cooled the furious attemptes and outragious inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of haultye <hi>Hanniball.</hi> In whoſe prayſe and commendacion, <hi>Enninus</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth theſe verſes following.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22986:15"/>
               <q>
                  <l>One man by protracting the time vvith delay.</l>
                  <l>Hath ſaued our vveale publique and reſtorde it again.</l>
                  <l>For he neuer forced, vvhat poyſoned tongues did ſay</l>
                  <l>So that his countrie in ſafetie might remaine.</l>
                  <l>Therefore his great glorie, and illuſtrious name,</l>
                  <l>Is regiſtred perpetuallie vvithin the booke of Fame.</l>
               </q>
               <p>What vigilancie &amp; what wiſedome vſed he, when <hi>Tarentine</hi> was delyuered to hym? I my ſelfe at that ſame tyme, when <hi>Salinator</hi> (who had loſte the towne and was ſledde into the caſtle) made his auaunt and proudly ſayd to <hi>Fabius</hi> theſe words. <hi>By my meanes it is come to paſſe: and me onely mayſt thou thanke <hi>O Fabius,</hi> for the recouerie and regaining of <hi>Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi>
                  </hi> hearde him whenne he ſmyled and made this aunſwere to him againe: It is euen true that thou ſayſte (quod hee) for if thou hadſt not loſte the Towne, I ſhold not haue recouered and wonne it. And vnto theſe his valiaunt exploites &amp; hardye actes in Martiall affaires moſte honourablie by warlicke proweſſe &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted courage, atchieued his graue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and wiſe counſaile in tyme of peace concerning ciuile ordinaunces and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22986:15"/>regiment, was in al poinctes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent, for when he was the ſecond time created Conſull, and his felowe in office <hi>Spurius Caruilius</hi> not intermedling with ſuch waightye buſines as to his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice were incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bent, neyther doing anye thing for the behoufe &amp; honor of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon wealthe, yet hee remembringe hys charge &amp; function reſiſted and with ſtode <hi>Caius Flaminius</hi> the plebeian tribune, to the vttermoſt of his power, who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the authoritie of the Senate pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumed &amp; taken vpon him, to diſtribute &amp; deuyde to euery one, man by man, al that piece of <hi>Italie</hi> that is called <hi>Picenum,</hi> and alſo that part of Fraunce that lyeth from the mountaines called <hi>Alpes</hi> to the riuer <hi>Rubicon.</hi> Alſo when he was <hi>Augur,</hi> hée wold not ſticke to ſay, that al ſuch things were fortunatly &amp; with good luck enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed &amp; taken in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which tended to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profite and behoufe of the comon wealth: &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted to endamage or blemiſh
<pb facs="tcp:22986:16"/>the ſoueraigne dignitie therof, were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckely &amp; in an ill time incepted. Many &amp; ſundry notable qualities haue I knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be incorporate in this noble ſage, but none more to be marueiled at, then how worthely &amp; pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly he toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his ſonne <hi>Marcus,</hi> who was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greatly for his deſerts renowmed &amp; had ben Conſul In whoſe praiſe and commendacion hée hath wryten a funerall Oracion, ryghte pithie and learned, which when we read, wée are ſo rauiſhed with the elegancie &amp; concinne vehemencie therof, that we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſay, that he ſurmounteth righte famous Oratours. Yea what Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher do we thinke able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare &amp; match wyth him? And his noblenes was not ſo much and ſo greatly blazed abrode in the open ſighte and hearinge of men, but his inculpable behauioure and vertuous dealinge was farre greater, and muche more to bée extolled, whiche he vſed pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatlye when he was at home and in hys owne houſe. What profounde talke vſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22986:16"/>hée? what ſappie ſentences vttered hée? what wholeſome preceptes and rules to lead our life by, ſhewed hée? how expert and conning was he in the monuments of Antiquitie? how exactlie was he ſéene in the art of diuinacion? yea: knowledge and ſkilfulnes was in him (as in a ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Romaine) great, exquiſite, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. He perfectly remembred and by hart coulde recoumpte all the warres and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploites as wel ciuill and domeſticall, as forraine and external. Whoſe talke and conference ſo greatly delighted my gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and thirſtie minde, as thoughe I had alreadie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iected &amp; deuined by an inward preſage, that which afterward chaunced, that when he dyed, I ſhoulde haue none nor fynd none, to reſorte vnto, for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile &amp; learnyng. But to what end do I ſpeake ſomuch of <hi>Maximus?</hi> Trulie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therby you may ſe, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is agret villainy, to ſay that ſuch an old age as his was, is wretched and miſerable. But all men can not bee <hi>Scipiones</hi> nor <hi>Maximi,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22986:17"/>to abuccinate and recompt what Cityes they haue ſacked, raſed and expugnated, to proclaime and tell abroad their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall conflicktes both by Sea and land, their warres victoriouſlye maintayned, their enterprices fortunately atchieued, nor their royal triumphes gloriouſly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnyzed. For when a man hath ledde his former life, quietly, vprightly, godly &amp; laudably, his old age is eaſie, myld, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and curteous, ſuch as the old age of <hi>Plato</hi> was,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plato</hi> died as hee ſatte writing.</note> who in the .lxxxi. yeare of his age, died as he ſat wryting. And ſuch was the old age of <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> who is ſaid, that he wrate his worke entituled <hi>Pana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenaicus,</hi> in the nynetye &amp; fourth yere of hys age, &amp; lyued fyue yeres after: whoſe Scholemayſter <hi>Leontinus Gorgias,</hi> liued fullye a hundreth and ſeuen yeares, and neuer faynted, drowped, nor gaue ouer his ſtudye and laboure whiche he had in hand. And when it was demaunded of him, why he would wiſh to liue ſo long: I haue (ſaid he) no cauſe whereby to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22986:17"/>or miſlike mine old age. Anotable anſwere and worthy to procéede oute of the mouth of a famous and learned man. For doltiſhe ſottes, and béetleheaded foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les do lay al their owne faults and blame vpon old age: which the prudente Poete <hi>Ennius,</hi> (of whom we lately made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whom you may wel remembre) vſed not to do. For he compareth his old age to the old age of a couragious Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer or victorious horſe in theſe wordes:
<q>
                     <l>Euen as a horſe of courage ſtoute</l>
                     <l>with comely porte and grace</l>
                     <l>VVhich oft hath born the bell, and vvone</l>
                     <l>The price in open race:</l>
                     <l>VVhen old age once with trembling pace</l>
                     <l>Hath him at length poſſeſt,</l>
                     <l>He ceaſſeth from ſuch frolicke feactes</l>
                     <l>And geeues him ſelfe to reſt.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Ennius</hi> I dare ſaye, you doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre well, For theſe twaine, <hi>T. Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius</hi> &amp; <hi>M. Attilius</hi> were created Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls the nynetenthe yere after his death,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:18"/>and he died when <hi>Caepio</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> wer the ſecond time Conſuls, being lxx. yeres old (for ſo long did he liue) at which time I being lxv. yeres old, with al my might and maine, and wyth an audible, &amp; firme voice, exhorted the people, that the Law called <hi>Lex Voconia</hi> might bée adiudged good, and effectuall and by Autenticke authorytie irreuocablie eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Ennius</hi> ſuſtayned and caried two ſuche burdens as are vulgarelie taken &amp; ſuppoſed to be the greateſt that can bée, that is to witte, <hi>Pouertie</hi> and Old age, yea and in ſuch ſorte, that he ſéemed in a maner to be highlie pleaſed, and therin to take great obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For in po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dering &amp; debating in my mind, I find that ther be foure principal cauſes, why Old age ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth wretched and miſerable. One is, becauſe therby a man is impeached and hindered from taking in hand any fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or charge in the comon wealth: an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, becauſe it enféebleth &amp; weakneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, the third is, becauſe it doth almoſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22986:18"/>take away al pleaſure &amp; laſciuious volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tée, &amp; the fourth is, becauſe it is not far of from death. Now iet vs (if you pleaſe) ſift &amp; diſcuſſe the force and validite of euerye one of theſe cauſes, and ſée how iuſt the allegacions of euerie of theym are. It hindreth and draweth a man backe, that he cannot do his affaires and buſineſſe, &amp; from the adminiſtracion of diuerſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from what buſineſſe and offices? fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as are by luſtines of youth &amp; bodily ſtrength atchieued? Are there no things appertainig to old men, which although their bodies be weak and féeble, yet may by the vigoure of the mind, be done &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred? Did <hi>Q. Fabius</hi> nothing? Did <hi>L. Paulus,</hi> who was thy father <hi>Scipio,</hi> &amp; the father in law of that worſhipful man my Sonne, nothing? And a great ſort of old men moe. The <hi>Fabritij,</hi> the <hi>Curij,</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runcani,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they maintained &amp; defended the weale publique with their graue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſailes &amp; authorities, did they nothing? <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piꝰ Claudiꝰ</hi> was not only old &amp; croked, but
<pb facs="tcp:22986:19"/>blind alſo: yet when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Senate wyth one accord, purpoſed to conclude a peace, and to condiſcende to a league with <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> he was not afraide to ſpeake thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des which <hi>Ennius</hi> in his verſes recited.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>VVhy do your wittes,</l>
                  <l>and ſenſes ſo raue?</l>
                  <l>VVhat fooliſhe conceipte,</l>
                  <l>doth encombre your braine?</l>
                  <l>VVhere bee the rype iudgementes,</l>
                  <l>vvhiche vvonte you vvere to haue?</l>
                  <l>To agree to your Countries,</l>
                  <l>ruyne moſt plaine?</l>
               </q>
               <p>And muche more purſueth hee in his <hi>Poeme,</hi> concerninge the ſame matter, whyche you knowe well ynoughe: And yet the Oracion which <hi>Appius</hi> made, is to be ſéene, whiche hee made ſeuentine yeares after his ſecond Conſulſhip, and betwene his two Conſulates ther were tenne yeres, and he had borne the office of Tenſor before his firſte Conſulate.</p>
               <p>Whereby it may be well perceyued &amp; ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22986:19"/>that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> inferred warre vpon the Romaines, he was a very aged man, and ſo haue we hearde our fathers and Progenitours reporte. Therefore their argument is weak and of no force, which ſay, that old age is not occupied in noble affaires and matters of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunce. And they do muche like, as if any man ſhould ſay that the Pylote and conductour of a ſhippe doth nothing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helpeth any thing in ſayling, when as ſome clymbe vp and ſit in the toppe of the Maſtes, ſome walk vpon the hatches, ſome clenſe the pumpe, but he holdinge the helme and ſtirring the rother, ſirteth quietlye in the ſterne or Puppe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he do not the ſame things, which yonge men doe, yet is his ſeruice farre better and greater then theirs. For mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of great waight, are not done wyth bodily ſtrength, nimblenes, celeritie and deliuerneſſe, but wythe counſaile, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, authoritie and pollicie, wherof old age accuſtomablye is not onelye not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryued,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:20"/>but rather therewith the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter increaſed, ſtored and furniſhed: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe peraduenture you thyncke, that I who haue bene bothe a Souldioure, a Tribune, a Marſhall of the fyelde, a Lieutenaunte of an armye, an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ adoure and a Conſull, and throughlye tryed in diuerſe bruntes and hazardes of warres, do nowe abandon all my former valyaunce, and geeue my ſelfe to Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to lyue vnprofytablye to the common wealthe, becauſe I haue ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſed frome warres and feactes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. But I do preſcribe ordres vnto the Senate, and ſhew to them what thinges in mine opinion are moſt expedient to be done, and géeue certaine informacion to them beforehand, how they maye make warre vpon the ſpightful <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> whoſe cancard harts haue a great while wiſhed &amp; contriued our confuſion, whoſe malicious ſtomaks I ſhal neuer ceaſe to feare, vntil I know perfectlye, that their proude Citye is diſtroyed, ruynated and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22986:20"/>vtterly ſubuerted. God graunte <hi>Scipio,</hi> that thou mayſte wynne the prayſe of that gloryous enterpryſe, and that it maye bée thy lotte, victoriouſlye to try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe ouer their vnſufferable inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, repreſſynge theyr treacherous haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyneſſe by fine force of armes and dente of Swearde, and that thou mayſt make a final ende of that, whych thy Graund-father made trybutarye: ſince whoſe deathe there are paſſed .xxxiii. yeares, but hys memoryall ſhall neuer bée for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, nor raſed oute of the myndes of all poſteritye. Hée dyed the yeare before I was Cenſour, nyne yeares after my Conſulſhyppe, whenne hée hadde béene elected and created Couſull the ſeconde tyme, I thanne hauynge the ſame office of Conſul. Thinke you that if hée hadde lyued tyll hée hadde béene a hundrethe yeare olde, hée woulde haue béene wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of hys Olde age? hée woulde not vſe to make roades and incurſyons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hys ennemyes terrytoryes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:21"/>he would not giue himſelfe to leaping, dauncing and ſkipping, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to caſt dartes and toſſe pikes a farre of, nor with ſweards to fighte and claſpe with his aduerſirie hand to hand, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to envre himſelf with wiſedom, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, conſultacion and iudgemente. Yf theſe poinctes had not bene in old men, our Predeceſſours woulde not haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſupremedignitie of counſailours, by the name of <hi>Senate.</hi> Amonge the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians</hi> they that bare the higheſte offices, as they be, ſo alſo are they called <hi>Auncients or Preſbiters.</hi> And if you bee diſpoſed, to heare and read forraine exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, you ſhall finde that noble and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſhinge common wealthes haue bene broughte to ruyne and ſeruitude by the vnripe adminiſtracion of vnſkilful yong men, and the ſame by old &amp; ſage fathers to haue bene maintayned, corroborated and recouered. Tell me this, howe loſte you your mighty and populous common wealth in ſo ſhorte ſpace? for to one that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22986:21"/>moued this queſtion and demaunde (as it is to bée ſéene in the Booke of the Poete <hi>Naeuius</hi> which he entituled <hi>Ludus</hi>) many anſweres were made and namely thys: <hi>There ſtepped forthe, nevve and ſtraunge Oratours, fooliſhe and light headed young-men, vvho bearing chiefe rule and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vvith their vnaduiſed counſailes and peuiſhe raſhnes haue brought our commune vvealthe to a miſerable ſtate and deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Raſhnes and temeritie is incidente to youthe, but prudence and pollicye to old age. But the memorie (you will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happes ſay) in old men faileth and wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth daylye worſe and worſe. I beleue it well, if a man do not vſe and exerciſe it, or if a man be of a dull and blockiſhe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> knew euery perſon in the Citie, and coulde cal euerye man by his proper name. Do you thinke, that in his old age, he vſed to name one man in ſtéede of another, and to ſalute <hi>Ariſtides</hi> in ſtede of <hi>Liſimachus.</hi> And I do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know them that ar yet aliue but their
<pb facs="tcp:22986:22"/>fathers &amp; Graundfathers alſo which are dead. Neither do I feare, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I read the <hi>Epitaphes</hi> and inſcripcions of Tombes &amp; graues, leaſt I ſhould therby, (as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credulity of people is) loſe my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and remembraunce: for in reading of them I am brought into remembraunce of thoſe that are deceaſſed. Neyther did I euer heare of any old man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> had ſo weak a memory to forget in what place he laid his purſe &amp; hidde his Treaſure. I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, they remember al ſuche thinges as they eſteme &amp; ſet ſtore by, they wil not ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glect nor forget their Obligacions, &amp; bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of debt, nor their dayes of apperaunce before anye Iuſticiarie, vnto whom they be indebted, &amp; who to them. They forget not what their counſailours in lawe do geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in charge, what their ordinaries &amp; Prelates eniogne to them, what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gurs</hi> do prognoſticate, &amp; what the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> do decide. Oh how many things do old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre? Old men haue their ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces &amp; wittes freſh &amp; vigorous ſo that they envre themſelues with exerciſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22986:22"/>Which thing is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly and dayly to be ſene not only in men of great calling &amp; honorable parentage, but alſo in priuate perſons &amp; haſkerds of low degrée, liuinge quietly <hi>Sophocles</hi> compyled &amp; made Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies, til he came to extreme old age, who being earneſtlye addicted to his ſtudies, was thoughte not to care or to take anye thought for his houſehold and domeſtical prouiſion, &amp; therfore was he ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly accuſed of his owne ſonnes, &amp; brought before the iudges, that they might defeate him from the vſe and poſſeſſion of his goods and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and that (as the cuſtome and maner is alſo among vs, when any do negligently loke to their buſineſſe, ſuffringe their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonye &amp; liuelyhode to fal in ruine &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye) the iudges mighte depoſe &amp; ſequeſtre him from the clayme &amp; vſe of his goods, as an old doting cockeſcom. But he vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge their ſubtile &amp; vnnatural dealinge, brought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hal, vnder his gowne a certaine Tragedie which he then had in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; had lately writen, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Oedipus Coloneus,</hi> &amp; red the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the iudges demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge of them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they thoughte that Poeme to argue
<pb facs="tcp:22986:23"/>any dotage in the writer? which when he had recited, he was by the ſentence of the Iudges acquited and diſcharged. Did old age cauſe this man, or <hi>Hiſiodus</hi> or <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nides,</hi> or <hi>Steſichorus,</hi> or <hi>Iſocrates</hi> or <hi>Gorgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> (of whom I ſpake before) or <hi>Homere,</hi> or the prince of Philoſophers <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, Democritus, Plato, Socrates,</hi> or of later dayes <hi>Zeno, Cleanthes,</hi> or <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Stoicke, whom you perſonallye ſaw at Rome, to fainte and quaile in their ſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or to be dryuen to ſuch a narowe iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue that they had not a word to ſay? was not the earneſt and infatigable agitaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all theſe mens ſtudies, equall to their life and conuerſacion? Go to, let vs omitte and ſpeake no more of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and abſtruſe ſtudies. I can name di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe vplandiſhe huſbandmen of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines,</hi> my neyghbours, and friendes, in whoſe abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ece their worke goeth ſo ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forward, that nothinge almoſt is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched about their huſbandrie, neyther in their tillage and ſowing of their corne
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22986:23"/>and fruictes, neyther in the gathering &amp; bringing theim into their Barnes: albe it in them this is not ſo much to be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed at. For ther is no man ſo old, but he thinketh that he may liue one yere lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger: and they toile about ſuche thynges, wherof they do wel know, that they ſhal not liue to enioy the profites. They plant and graffe trées which ſhal yelde fruicte, not to theym, but to their ſucceſſion and poſteritie, as our <hi>Statius</hi> in his booke cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Synaephebis</hi> declareth. And if any huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (be he neuer ſo old) be demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and aſked, to whoſe behoufe he graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth and ſoweth, he wil not ſticke to ſay: I ſowe for the immortal Goddes, whoſe pleaſure was, that I ſhould not receyue profittes fruictes and emolumentes at the handes of my Predeceſſours but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiuelie and condicionally to leaue, ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rendre &amp; redeliuer the ſame or as much to my ſucceſſours. The ſaying of <hi>Caeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> which went afore, touching old men that laboured and prouided for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele
<pb facs="tcp:22986:24"/>and ſucceſſion, is farre better, then this followinge which he alſo wryteth: <hi>Certes, although old age vvhen it cometh, had none other inconuenience nor greuau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ioyned with it yet this one is grefe ynough, becauſe by liuing long, a man ſeeth many things? vvhich he vvould not ſe.</hi> But I ſay &amp; replye to it, that peraduenture he ſéeth many things which he is right glad and willing to ſe. And it ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times happeneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is yong mens lot, to ſée ſuch things, as they are loth to ſée. But this next ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame <hi>Caecilius</hi> is as il, or rather worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the abſurde ſentence y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wents before. I iudge &amp; repute (ſayth he) this in old age to be moſte miſerable, becauſe a man perceiueth himſelf in that age, to be odious to them of yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger yeres. But I ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age is rather pleaſaunte then odious. For euen as old aged men, being wiſe &amp; vertuous, take great pleaſure &amp; delighte in the compaignie of toward &amp; godly nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured yongmen, wherby their old age vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them ſéemeth the more facile &amp; tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe they ſe themſelues reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22986:24"/>of youth: So likewiſe yongmen haue great comfort &amp; contentacion in the hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome leſſons and pithie preceptes which they heare of old men, wherby their min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des are enflamed &amp; ſtirred to folow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; embrace honeſtie. And I do not ſée the contrarie, but you for your parts take as much pleaſure &amp; are as glad of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paignie, as I am of yours. Now you plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſée, that old age is not only frée from al ſlouthful drowſines, &amp; faint fée blenes, but is rather occupied and buſied in lawdable exerciſes, doing euer ſom thing, deuiſing &amp; excogitating ſuch matters, as euery one in the freſh yeres of his former luſty age, was moſte envred withal. Yea they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe &amp; augmente their knowledge, and leerne ſtil more &amp; more, as we haue ſene by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble Lawmaker <hi>Solon,</hi> who great lye reioyced &amp; in certain verſes gloried, ſaying, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he waxed euery day an old man, by encreaſing his knowledge &amp; learning daylie ſomwhat more, then he knew be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I my ſelfe alſo did, for I learned the Gréeke tongue whenne I was an
<pb facs="tcp:22986:25"/>old man. Which with ſuch earneſt ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and inexpleble gréedines I learned or rather ſnatched vnto me, (albeit in my youth I vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned it) as thoughe it had béene a man muche deſyringe to quenche his longe and drie thriſte. And this I did to the entent I might aſpire &amp; attaigne to the vnderſtandyng and ſkyll of thoſe things, whych you now ſée me to vſe for examples. And when I heard ſay, that <hi>Socrates</hi> in his old dayes did the ſame in Muſicall Inſtrumentes, I was alſo deſirous to haue done the like (for in old time, men commonly learned to play on Inſtruments) but in humanity and learnynge I trauayled diligently and toke paynes therin ful ſtudiouſly.</p>
               <p>And now I do no more deſire to haue the ſtrength of a youngma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (for this was the ſecond diſpraiſe and faulte that was laied againſt old age) then I did when I was younge, deſire to haue had the force and ſtrength of a Bul or an Olyphant. For what ſoeuer is engraffed naturally
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22986:25"/>in man, that is it fitte and decent to vſe, and in al thinges that he taketh in hand to labour &amp; to do his diligente endeuour, accordinge to his ſtrengthe. For what words can there bée more contemptible, ſhameful, and abiect, then thoſe of <hi>Milo Crotoniata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Milo</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayſed for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayling his lacke of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth in his old age.</note> who being old &amp; ſeinge ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye Champions and wreſtlers exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them ſelues and tryinge their force in the running place or field of exerciſe, is reported that he beheld his owne ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and ſaid wéeping. <hi>Alas,</hi> theſe armes of mine that once were ſtrong and muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, are now dead? O thou vaine and light witted man, what a beaſt art thou to ſpeake ſuch fooliſh words? thy Armes are not ſo much deade, as thou arte thy ſelf. For thou ſéekeſt no fame, renowme and glory by thy ſelfe, but by thy bodely ſtrengthe and the highe bigneſſe of thy Armes and ſydes. Such fonde and vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed wordes neuer proceded out of the mouth of <hi>Sextus Aemilius,</hi> nor <hi>T. Corun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> that was many yeares before, nor
<pb facs="tcp:22986:26"/>of <hi>P. Craſſus,</hi> ſince their dayes who were men of greate authority and wiſedome, who alſo appoincted &amp; preſcribed lawes and ordres for the Romaynes: whoſe prudence perſeuered and honourably co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued til the very laſt houre of death. But I am afrayde,<note place="margin">An ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</note> leaſte an Oratoure through impotencie and debylitie of old age, muſt be forced to quaile and ſtay fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the practiſe of his profeſſion, becauſe his office and function conſiſteth not only in wytte and eloquence, but alſo in a loude durableneſſe, and ſtrainable voice, with other circumſtaunces belonging to vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce. This ſhril and audible tenour of ſpeach &amp; pronunciacion, forſaketh not an old man, no not in the extremetie of his age, but as a moſte beautifull grace (I know not how) doth accompaignie him to the end, Which I haue neyther loſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I thinke my ſelfe to be deſtitute of, and yet you both doſe my gray heares and my auncientie of yeres. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, a curteous and mylde ſpeach, and a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22986:26"/>gentle, quiet or temperate vtterau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſeth the beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hearts of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and much commendeth the partie in whome they are incorporate, yea a ſmoth and learned Oratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoken by an eloquent old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, greatly deliteth the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and maketh them attentiue. And although a man can not do theſe things himſelfe, yet maye he inſtruct <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Laelius,</hi> and other towarde younge men. For what thinge is ſo pleaſaunt, as old age, guarded and enuironed with honeſt and ſtudious yongmen, being preſt, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and deſirous to ſhew and do their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obedience &amp; dutiful reuerence? Shall we debarre old age from hauing autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and power to teach, enfourme, chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe &amp; admoniſh youth to do their duties, and to traine or frame them in vertuous dreade and godlye knowledge? Thanne which office, what can be more excellent or honourablye? Verelye, me thoughte that <hi>Caius</hi> and <hi>P. Scipio,</hi> and thy two Graunde fathers, <hi>L. Aemelius</hi> and <hi>P.
<pb facs="tcp:22986:27"/>Africanus</hi> were happy and fortunate, by reaſon of the daylye compaignie of yong Gentlemen. And they whych are may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and profeſſours of the liberal artes and ſciences are to be taken and accomp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted no other wiſe, but bleſſed and fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: yea althoughe their ſtrength and firme luſtines of their bodies be decaied and imbecilled: albeit, this ſame decaye and fayling of the natural ſcrength doth oftener happen, through the default of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doleſcencie then of old age. For a libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and incontinent life, laſcyuiouſlye and inordinatly lead in youth, euer brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and deliuereth to olde age, a féeble, weake and impotent bodie. But kinge <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Goodlye examples of noble perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</note> of whome <hi>Xenophon</hi> writeth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge other his talke which he had, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his deathe bed, being a very olde man, ſayeth, that he neuer felte nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued his old age anye whitte weaker or féebler then his adoleſcency and youth was. When I was a boy, I remembre <hi>L. Metellus,</hi> who after he had bene twyſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22986:27"/>Conſul, and foure yeres after his ſecond Conſulate, was elected &amp; created <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prelate</hi> or high Prieſt, (which Prelacie &amp; Prieſthoode he enioyed xxii. yeares) had in his olde age ſuche corporall ſtrength, that he neuer ſéemed to deſire or care for his adoleſcencie. I néede not héere to ſpeake any thing of my ſelf, although (if I ſhould) it were but the propertie of vs old men, and is by the priuiledge and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of our age to vs permitted. Do you not ſée how oftentimes <hi>Neſtor</hi> doth cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate and extoll his owne vertues, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and recordinge his owne approued valiaunce, ioyned wythe prudence and pollicy, and bluſſhed not, with his owne mouth to make therof a moſt honorable mencion, as in <hi>Homere</hi> it is moſt many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly to be ſéene? He lyued thrée mens ages, and neded not to feare,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Neſtor</hi> liued ccc. yeres.</note> leaſt in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing and ſoundinge oute of his owne prayſes, he ſhould be thought either ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant or vainelie talkatiue For as <hi>Ho: mere</hi> wryteth and teſtifieth of him, there
<pb facs="tcp:22986:28"/>iſſued and proceded oute of his mouthe moſte cloquente ſpeache, and ſugred woordes, ſwéeter then Honye, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teraunce and declaracion of whyche his Pithye and pleaſaunte counſayles, hée néeded not anye robuſteous force of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delye ſtrengthe:<note place="margin">Wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellethe ſtrength.</note> and yet <hi>Agamemnon</hi> Prince of <hi>Graecia</hi> and chyefe generall of all thoſe warlyke exploytes, neuer wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to haue tenne perſonnes, lyke to <hi>Aiax,</hi> but hée manye tymes wyſſhed that hée hadde had tenne ſuche as <hi>Neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> was: Sayinge furthermore, that if hée hadde ſo manye <hi>Neſtors,</hi> hée woulde not doubte but that Troye ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſhorte ſpace hee vtterlye ruynated and deſtroyed. But nowe to retourne and ſaye ſomewhat of my ſelfe. I am nowe goynge on my lxxxiii. yeare, and woulde to God, that I myghte make my vaunte, and glorye in that, for whyche <hi>Cyrus</hi> dydde in manner tryumphe and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22986:28"/>thynke hym ſelfe happye: but yet thys canne I ſaye, that althoughe I haue not ſuche ſtrengthe as I hadde whenne I was a Souldyoure at the fyrſte war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res betweene the Romaynes and the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> or as I hadde, whenne I was in the ſame warres, in the offyce of Queſtor or generall receyuer, or as I hadde, whenne I was Conſull in Spayne, or as I hadde foure yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whenne I was deputed Marſhall, of the fyelde, and foughte a battayle, wherein I dyſcomfayted the populons armye of proude <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and others of oure ſtyffenéecked Ennemyes that hadde encamped theymſelues in Baſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and Garryſons vppon the toppe of the greate Mountaynes and Strayctes called <hi>Thermopylae: Marcus Attilius,</hi> and <hi>C. Labeo</hi> beynge at that tyme
<pb facs="tcp:22986:29"/>Conſuls: yet al theſe hazards and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conflictes notwithſtanding, olde age hath not throughly afflicted neither altogether debilitated and exhauſted me. For neither the Senate, neither the <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> and Iudgemente Hall, neither my friendes and clientes, neyther my Gue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and ſtraungers (whom by the law of Hoſpitality I am bound and ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend) do find them ſelues deſtitute of my help, neither do eſpie any default or lack of ſtrength to be in me. And I neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended nor agreed to this old approued prouerbe, of moſt men praiſed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, which willeth, that who ſo euer deſyreth to be an old man longe,<note place="margin">This pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſom freſh water Souldy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our a gret deale fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Carpet thenne a Campe.</note> ſhoulde begin to be an old man betime &amp; quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as who would ſay, that he ſhould now in his flouriſhinge and freſhe age deſiſt from trauaile and labour wherin youth delighteth, and altogether to prouide for eaſe and conſeruacion of his health. But I had leifer not to be an old man longe, then to be an old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before I wer old in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22986:29"/>deede. And therfore ther was neuer man yet to this day, that can ſay, that he euer came to ſpeake with me, but he found me occupied and doing ſomewhat. But I do confeſſe, that I haue not ſo much bodily ſtrength as either of you twaine hath: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, neither of you, hath the ſtrength of <hi>T. Pontius</hi> the Centurio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What then? is he therefore nobler and better then you are? Let ther be a moderacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſtrength and let euery man attempt and aſſaie ſo much as he is wel able to compaſſe, and he that doth this, ſhal féele no great wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſtrength, nor be agreued for the lacke thereof. In the famous games of <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> it is ſayd that the ſtrong Champion <hi>Milo</hi> cam in, carying on his ſhoulders a huge and bigge bodied Bull aliue, and bare him a furlong of: now, if thou were put to thy choiſe, whether haddeſte thou leifer haue the bodelye ſtrength of thys <hi>Milo,</hi> or els the quickenes of witte and the inward vertues of mynd, whiche the noble Philoſopher <hi>Pythagoras</hi> had? In
<pb facs="tcp:22986:30"/>fine, vſe and take well in woorthe thys gyfte of bodily ſtrength, whyle thou haſt it, and when it is gone, do not deſyre nor ſéeke to haue it again, vnleſſe peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you wyl ſay, that yonge men ought to wyſhe theim ſelues in theyr infancye and ſwathynge bandes againe, or when they be ſomwhat further ſtryken in yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and in the maturitie or beſte tyme of their age, to wiſhe them ſelues agayne in theyr adoleſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. The race and courſe of age is certayne, and there is but one way of nature and the ſame ſimple, and to euery part of a mans life and age, are géeuen hys conuenyente tymes and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre tempeſtiuytyes. For euen as weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and infirmytie is incident to yonge Chyldren, a luſtynes and brauerie to younge men, and a grauitye when they come to rype yeares: ſoe lykewyſe the maturitye or rypenes of olde age, hathe a certaine ſpeciall gifte, géeuen and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trybuted to it by nature, whych oughte not to bée neglected, but to bée taken in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22986:30"/>hys due tyme and ſeaſon when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. I thincke <hi>Scipio,</hi> that you heare by report, what your Hoſte, the moſte faithful confederate to the Romayn peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Maſiniſſa</hi> kynge of <hi>Mauritania</hi> doth now a dayes, beynge lxxxx. yeares olde.<note place="margin">A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of a valtaunt &amp; father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prince.</note> For whenne hee taketh anye voyage or iourneye, goinge at the firſt on foote, hée wyll not for that iourney ride nor come on horſebacke: and contrarywiſe, when hée rydeth foorthe on horſebacke, hée ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vſéeth to alyghte of frome his horſe: no tempeſtuous weather, no ſtormes, nor colde canne make him to couer hys heade, but euer goethe bareheade hys bodye is ſoe drye, that hee is neuer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted with anye ſuch corrupt humoures as old men commonlye are infected and encombred withall, and therefore doothe hee in his owne perſonne execute al the offyces and functions that to a royall and noble Kynge do appertayne. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore exercyſe, moderate dyete and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy
<pb facs="tcp:22986:31"/>are able to conſerue ſomwhat of a mans luſtines and former ſtrength, yea and that in olde age. Ther is (ſome ſay) no ſtrength in olde age: I anſwere that ſtrength is not required of old age, Therefore by the lawdable lawes and. holeſome ordinaunces, which our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours haue for ciuill order and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vtilitie enacted, our age is diſpenced withall, exempted and diſcharged from al ſuche affaires as can not be withoute bodily ſtrength ſuſtayned and accompliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Wherby we are not compelled to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, which we are vnable to perfourme, yea wee are borne withall and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to doe ſo much as we can do. But you wil againe obiect and ſay: Many old men are ſoe weake and feble, that they are not able to execute and diſcharge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye office or function that belongeth to mans life, and ſerueth for maintenance of vertue in humaine ſocietie. But truly the cauſe therof is not proprely to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the old age, but commonelye to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22986:31"/>lacke of health. What a weake and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent man was the ſonne of <hi>P. Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> euen hee, that made thee his ſonne by adoption? was not he ſo often aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and attained with diſcraſies and ſick neſſe, that hee was in a maner neuer healthful? which if it had otherwiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, vndoubtedly he would haue proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſeconde Myrroure and the moſte precious Iewel or ornament of our Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nexte vnto his noble father. For to counteruaile the haute courage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comarable proweſſe of his ſaide father, he was furniſſhed with greater learning and more abundant giftes of the mynd. What meruaile is it therfore in old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if now and then, they be ſicke and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſith youngmen alſo are ſubiect to the ſame, and can not warrant them ſelues of health, no more then oldme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can? We muſt (deare frends <hi>Laelius</hi> and <hi>Scipio</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt old age, and the inconueniences and faultes therof, muſt by diligence be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced and amended. And euen as
<pb facs="tcp:22986:32"/>we muſte arme oure ſelues to fighte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte infirmities and ſickneſſe, ſo alſo muſte wee ſtriue againſte old age. Wee muſt haue a good eye and a diligent reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to our health, and we muſt vſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate exerciſes of the bodye. We muſt not be to ingluvious,<note place="margin">Prccep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to be Welwai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed and obſerued on al ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> in taking our foode and repaſte, wee muſte not pamper and gourmandiſe our ſelues withe exceſſe of meate and drinke, but ſo much and ſuch competencie thereof muſte be taken, as ſufficeth to refreſhe the vitall powers and naturall ſtrengthe, and not to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, hebetate, and vtterly to extinguiſh them. And we muſt not haue regarde to helpe the bodie onelye, but muche more to maintaine and conſerue the Memorie and reaſonable parte of man, whyche is the mind. For theſe are vtterlie defaced, extint and ſuffocated throughe to muche gluttinge fare, and rauenous ingurgita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And euen as a Lampe, if to muche oyle bee infuſed into it, burnethe not brightly, but yeldeth a very dymme and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22986:32"/>darkiſhe lighte, againe, if it lacke oyle, it lacketh alſo lighte: ſoe likewiſe the mind is a like dulled &amp; blunted, when the body is either ouercharged wyth ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aboundance and ſurfette, or els reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned from the ſuffciencie that nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. In olde age, naturall ſtrengthe eyther by defatigatyon, or els by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much and vehement exerciſe drowpeth, and waxeth lumpiſhe and vnweldy: but the promptitude or readines of the wit and minde, is by beinge exerciſed, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whetted and ſharpened. For thoſe old men whom the comical Poete <hi>Caecilius</hi> calleth fooliſhe, he meaneth to be ſuch as are credulous and light of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, forgetful, remiſſe, diſſolute and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glygent about theyr buſineſſe, which are not the propre vyces and peculier faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Olde age it ſelfe, but of ſuche an Olde age, as is ſlouthefull, ſluggiſhe, drowſie, and géeuen more to ſleape and bellye théere, then to any good and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable exerciſe.
<pb facs="tcp:22986:33"/>And as petulancie, malepertnes, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidinous volupte bee vices ſoner to bee founde in younge men then in old men, (&amp; yet al yong men are not ſurpriſed nor ſnared with thoſe beaſtly baites, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuche, as are of naughtie diſpoſition &amp; vnthriftie natures) ſo this foliſhnes that entangleth and captiuateth the ſenſes of old men (which is commonly called Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) is not in al old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but in thoſe only which are light witted, &amp; kepe not them ſelues wythin the limittes of reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Appius</hi> being beſide his extreme olde age alſo blind, ruled and kept in awe his foure tall ſonnes, fiue daughters, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milye and houſehold (which was great) and entended the Patronage of his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliaunt clientes, For he had his minde bent like a Bow, and neuer ſhronke for his yeres, neither ſuffred he Old age to haue the victory ouer him. He reſerued &amp; kept his authoritye ouer all theym, that were vnder hys charge, and his family was ready at his becke and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22986:33"/>his ſeruaunts feared him, his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren houored and reuerenced him, and al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entierly loued him. In his houſehold the cuſtomes of his noble pedagrew and Aunceſtours, and the diſciplyne of hys Countrie toke place effectuallye. For herein is Old age honeſt and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: in defendinge and mayntayninge it ſelfe, in retayninge and kéepinge his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorytie, in ſauing it ſelfe frée from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſeruitude, and in exerciſinge rule and authorytie ouer them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his charge, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntil the laſt houre of death. And as we do commend a younge man in whom appeareth any grauitie &amp; rypenes of wytte, which to elder age ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth more incidente: ſo likewiſe do wee prayſe that old man, which hath ſome of the qualyties and propreties of a younge man of honeſte and ſobre demeanoure, which thinge who ſo euer marketh and foloweth, maye be old in bodye, but hée ſhal neuer be old in minde. I haue nowe in hande the ſeuenth booke of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:34"/>and firſte foundacions of all the rityes in Italie, I do collecte and gather into one volume, all the notable monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of antiquity, and now preſently I am aboute the finiſſhinge of an other Booke, wherein ſhalbe contayned the Oracions of all ſuche famous cauſes, as I haue in my time defended. I am a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtudiente and practyſer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Augurs</hi> lawe, the Canon, and the ciuyll Lawe. I géeue my ſelfe muche to the Gréeke tongue, and to exercyſe my memorye wythall,<note place="margin">A nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> memory.</note> I doe as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> Scholers were wonte to doe: for what ſoe euer I haue harde, ſpoken or done the daye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I call to remembraunce and debate the ſame with myſelfe in the euenynge. Theſe are the exerciſes of the wytte, theſe are the feates wherein the mynde is occupied, and theſe are the agitacions wherby it is ſtirred to vertuous opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. I géeuing my ſelfe to theſe trades, and therein labouringe neceſſauntlye, doe not greatlye lacke, neyther thinke
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22986:34"/>my ſelfe deſtitute of bodelye ſtrengthe. When my friendes ſtand in néede of my ayde and helpe, I am preeſte and readye to ſtande them in ſtéede, I vſe many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to come into the Senate, and vnaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked I alledge and bringe many reaſons whyche wyth longe ſtudy I haue before premeditated and the ſame doe I mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, vpholde, defende and ſupporte, not by ſtrengthe of bodye but of mynd. Yea although I were not able in proper per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne to execute and put things in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe, yet ſhoulde I lyinge in my bedde, take greate pleaſure and delyte, by thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng and conſidering how to deuiſe and compaſſe thinges which I could not doe. But the life whyche heretofore I haue ledde, hathe bene and is ſuche, that I am able and canne do theym. For vnto him that ſpendeth hys tyme in ſuche labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and ſtudies, old age is not perceiued when and howe it ſtealeth vppon him. Thus age waxeth old, and by lytle and lytle declineth as it weare inſenſiblye,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:35"/>and it is not ſodainly amputated, or cut of, but by longe continnaunce and diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnytie, is lyke a lampe, quenched and extinguiſſhed.</p>
               <p>Now foloweth the third diſprayſe and fault which is layed in olde age, becauſe (ſaye they) it is wythoute pleaſure, and muſte forgoe voluptuous appetites. O noble and excellent gift, wherwith Old age is ſoe bleſſed, if it take frome vs that thing, which is in youth moſte vicious &amp; deteſtable. But you (noble and vertuous gentlemen <hi>Scipio</hi> &amp; <hi>Laelius</hi>) heare what <hi>Architas</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous Philoſopher of <hi>Taren to,</hi> was wont to ſay, whoſe Oration tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame matter was lent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to me, when I was a yong man and ſerued vnder <hi>Q. Maximus</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Tarento.</hi> He ſayd, that no plague was géeuen by nature ſo great and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious vnto men, as the beſtiall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and voluptuouſnes of the bodye. Which pleaſures, the diſſolute and libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous luſtes of men do ſo much affecte
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22986:35"/>and deſire, that with all licentious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanacion and outrage, their minds bée incyted and ſtirred to purſue the ſame, thinking al thinges lawful for their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brideled appetites, ſo that they maye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their beaſtly deſires and ſtill wallow in the fylthie puddle of their helliſh ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie. Hence (ſaide he) as from a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine do ſpring out al kinds of miſchief, as Treaſon, betraying of countraies, the ruyne and ſubuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of comon wealthes, ſecret conuenticles and priuye conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with the enemyes:<note place="margin">Pleaſure is the bayte of al miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> finally (he ſayde) there was none ſo greate a villanie, nor anye ſo flagitious and horrible an enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitye, whyche the inordinate deſyre of pleaſure would not egge and pricked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde mens frowarde willes to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe: furthermore that whoredome, adul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie and all ſuche like heynous factes of carnall concupiſcencie were by noone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lures or enticements proucked but by pleaſure. And whereas eyther nature or god hath géeuen vnto man nothing of
<pb facs="tcp:22986:36"/>ſo noble excellencye as the mynd or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſoule, there is nothing ſo greate an ennemye vnto this ineſtimable and deuyne gift, as pleaſure, For wher plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure beareth ſwaye and ruleth the roſte, there is no manſion nor dwellyng place lefte for Temperaunce and Sobrietye, and to bée ſhort, vertue can not remaine where pleaſure raigneth. Which thing, that it myght the better be vnderſtanded and more euidentlye bee perceyued, hée badde, that a man ſhould ymagine and in bys mynde preſuppoſe ſome manne to bee captiuated, ouerwhelmed and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together plunged in as muche of this beaſtly Pleaſure as he coulde conceiue: whyche beinge doone, he thought there would bée no man whoſe ſenſes were ſo muche bounde vppe in the vaile of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, but bee woulde eaſelye iudge, that ſuche a man, ſo long as hys mynde was thus paſſionated, wyth ſuche bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe and filthye affections, coulde not contryue or compaſſe any honeſt action,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22986:36"/>nor rule him ſelfe by reaſon and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie. And therfore, ther is nothing ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent, ſo execrable and hurtful as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. For if it ſhoulde enter into mans hart and there longe bare dominacion, it would quighte marre, deface and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe al the light of the mind, which is reaſon and vnderſtandynge. <hi>Nearchus</hi> in whoſe houſe I lodged in <hi>Tarento,</hi> whoe alſo ſheewed him ſelfe verie friendlye to the Romaine people, ſayd, that he hadde heard his aunceſtours and elders report, that <hi>Architas</hi> ſpake al theſe words, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Romayne Conſuls <hi>P. Poſthumius</hi> &amp; <hi>T. Veturius</hi> were diſcomfited and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen by the <hi>Samnites,</hi> who had enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned and entrapped them like fiſhes in a nette or Buckes in a Buckſtall in the perillous ſtraytes and difficile entries of <hi>Caudium. C. Pontius</hi> the valiaunt <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> and his father being then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours and captaines general of the <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> armie. <hi>Plato</hi> alſo the noble <hi>A theni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Philoſopher, was preſent &amp; heard him
<pb facs="tcp:22986:37"/>ſpeake theſe wordes, whom I do in olde hiſtories fynd, that he came and arriued at <hi>Tarento,</hi> when <hi>L. Aemilius</hi> and <hi>Appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Claudius</hi> were Conſuls. But to what purpoſe do al theſe circumſtancies tend? Trulye that you may vnderſtande, if we cannot be perſwaded by reaſon and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to abandonne our wantonnes and mortifye oure pleaſures, yet that we are muche bounden and beholdinge to olde age, by whoſe meanes we are ſo tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately diſpoſed, that we haue no luſte to do any thing, which is vndere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be done. For pleaſure being a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and mortall enemye to reaſon, hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vertuous action and prudent conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, and the eyes of the mind thereby are ſo iuggled and bewitched, that it can haue no felowſhip nor compaignie with vertue. Sore againſt my wil was it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I depoſed and dyſgraded <hi>L. Flaminius,</hi> (brother to the worthye and hardie gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman <hi>T. Flaminius</hi>) of his ſenatourſhip. ſeuen yeares after hee had bene Conſul:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22986:37"/>but yet I well conſidered and wyth my ſelfe waighed, that it was expedient and needefull that his lawleſſe and vicious déede ſhould not eſcape due puniſhment, becauſe impunitie manye times doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimate men of ſemblable diſpoſition an other time to bee the bolder to attempte further miſchiefe by geuing the bridle to their owne licentious will and ſenſuall affections. For when hée was apoincted Conſul in <hi>Lumbardie,</hi> he was at the citie of <hi>Placence,</hi> requeſted by a Curtiſaine or common harlott at a banquet,<note place="margin">Gallica Ciſaiona</note> to cauſe ſome one of his captiues whom hée had taken and kepte in priſon and adiudged to dye) to be preſently in her ſight behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, becauſe the bloudy Strumpet (as ſhe ſayd) had neuer ſéene any executed: vnto whoſe deſire and requeſte he relented, &amp; forthwith commaunded one of theym to be put to death. And duringe the time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his brother <hi>Titus</hi> was Cenſor, (whyche dignitye he enioyed next before me) hée eſcaped, and was neuer therefore puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.
<pb facs="tcp:22986:38"/>But when I and <hi>Flaccus</hi> wer made Cenſors, we could not brooke ſuch enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytie nor wynke at ſuche a ſelfe willed exaumple, becauſe he abuſed and blemiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the honoure of our noble Empyre, with hys priuate lewdnes and ſhameful ſenſualitie. I haue oftentymes hearde our elders ſay, (whych they alſo as they reported, had heard of their fathers and old predeceſſours when they wer boyes) that <hi>C. Fabritius</hi> was wont much to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naile, becauſe on a tyme when hee was ſent on an Ambaſſade to <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> kynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Epyrotes,</hi> he heard one <hi>Cyneas</hi> (who was borne in <hi>Thaſſalia</hi> and was the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Scholemaſter) report and tel, how y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther was a certain man of <hi>Athens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epicures</note> which profeſſed himſelf to be a wiſe man, &amp; ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al our actions, thoughts &amp; dedes what ſo euer they were, oughte to be referred only to pleaſure, as to the principal end, repoſing therin our chiefeſt felicitie. <hi>M. Curius</hi> and <hi>T. Coruncanus,</hi> hearyng this abhominable aſſertion and deuiliſh opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22986:38"/>whiche <hi>Fabricius</hi> tolde, oftentymes wiſſhed that the <hi>Samnites,</hi> and <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> himſelfe, were reſolued and perſwaded to beléeue and credite the wordes of that prophane helhounde: becauſe if they would enthral and addict them ſelues to diſporte daliaunce, vanitie and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they might the ſoner be conquered, and their proude ſtomackes appaulled. This <hi>M. Curiꝰ</hi> liued with <hi>P. Decius,</hi> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that in his fourth Conſulſhippe, fiue yeeres before the Conſulate of <hi>Curius,</hi> voluntarily gaue himſelfe to deathe for the ſafegarde and preſeruacion of hys Countrie. <hi>Fabricius</hi> knew hym, &amp; ſo did <hi>Coruncanus</hi> alſo, who aſwell by their owne lyfe, as by thys woorthye facte of <hi>Decius</hi> of whome I nowe ſpake, iudged and thought that there was ſomethinge naturallye good, fayre, excellente, and for it ſelfe onely expetible, which euery good and vertuous man ſhold and ought to loue, honour &amp; embrace, abandoning and vilipending al ſenſual pleaſure and
<pb facs="tcp:22986:39"/>looſe diſhoneſtie. But to what purpoſe do we ſpeake ſo much of pleaſure? Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to thintent that hereby it may be ſene and proued, how that it can not onelye, not be obiected to Old age for any vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and diſpraiſe, but rather for a ſiuguler prayſe and commendacion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe old age dothe not eſtéeme nor care for theſe pleaſures. But ſome other wil ſaye: It lacketh ſumptuous fare, coſtlye diſhes, delicate viande, and drinkes of all ſortes: Hereto I aunſwere, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it lacketh alſo dronkennes, cruditie or indigeſtion, phantaſtical dreames and ridiculous apparitions. But if we muſt any whitte yeld to pleaſure (becauſe we cannot eaſily reſiſt the blandiments and allurementes therof, (for the deuine phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher <hi>Plato</hi> calleth pleaſure the baite of all miſchiefe,<note place="margin">Pleaſure the bayte of al miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</note> becauſe men therewithe are caught and ſnared euen as fiſhes are wyth the hooke) I ſaye, that althoughe old age be not endaungered nor géeuen to ſuperfluous and immoderate banque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22986:39"/>and at vnſeaſonable houres, yet in temperate and moderate feaſting it may be ſolaced and comfortablye recreated. I my ſelfe when I was a boy, haue often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſene <hi>C. Duillius</hi> the Soune of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus,</hi> (the ſame that firſte vanquiſhed the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> in terrible fighte on the Sea) retourne home being an olde man from the place where he hadde ſupped: hee woulde manye times haue a linke or a toorche caried before hym, and a mynſtrell alſo playinge on a ſhaulme, whiche no pryuate perſon before hym e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer did: his warlicke exploites and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant victoryes ſhold (as he thought) be to him for this licentious libertie and new begonne cuſtome, a ſufficient war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiſe. But to what ende doe I recite ſo much of others? I wyl now ſpeake ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of my ſelfe: firſte I haue alwaies had ſome of my compaignions and fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des at my table, when I toke my ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie repaſte. For the order of fraternities and aſſemblies of honeſte and ſobre per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:40"/>moderately to ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quet one with an other was inſtituted and made when I was <hi>Queſtor,</hi> and for the more regall furniture and pompous ſolemnizacion of this Ceremonie, the image or picture of <hi>Cybele</hi> who is called the mother of the Goddes, with al the rites and obſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therto belonging was broughte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uaighed to Rome out of <hi>Phrygia.</hi> I ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore moderatlye banqueted and within the bondes of ſobrietie I vſed to ſolace my ſelfe, &amp; merylie to make good chéere with my Coequalls. But I was then, in the luſtie floures of myne age, and there was in me a certaine heate of Iuuenili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whiche (as age groweth and encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) is qualefied, and al things brought to a conueniente and tractable decencie. Neither did I take delectacion in theſe banquettes and epulacions for bodelye pleaſure and glutting gourmandyſe, but rather for the compaignye and talke of my frendes and welwillers. Therfore oure elders and predeceſſours did verye
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22986:40"/>wel, to terme a banquet or feaſt, wherat frends do meat together, by the name of <hi>Conuiuium:</hi> becauſe it hath a coniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of liuing together one with an other, &amp; therin they termed it much better then the Gréekes do, for the name which they géeue it, ſignifieth as much as a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion,<note place="margin">Sympo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium.</note> as though frends méete together purpoſely to quaffe and drinke: And a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cenacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or a comeſſation, as though they aſſembled for the chéere or the meates ſake: wherin they ſeme to alow &amp; comend that moſt,<note place="margin">Synep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium</note> whiche is the leſt parte of the goodnes that therein is to be taken. But I am delyted in feaſtes and banquettes beinge made in ſeaſonable and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente times, for the ſolace and pleaſure whyche I take in learned conference and colloquyes of wyſedome, and that not onely wyth my equalles and theym that are of the ſame age that I am, (wherof the numbre is now verye fewe and ſmall) but alſo wyche you twayne, and other younge gentlemen of freſher
<pb facs="tcp:22986:41"/>yeres, And I hartely thanke old age for this boone &amp; good turne, becauſe it hathe increaſed in me an earneſt deſire of talk, and debatinge of ſerious matters withe men of approued learning and grauytie, but the gréedie deſire of meat and drinke it hath taken awaye from me: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if any old man bee delighted in theſe blandiments of pleaſure (I meane good chéere &amp; daintie fare, (leaſt I ſhould ſéeme to ſtand at open defiaunce and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce warre to all pleaſure, whereof peraduenture ther is ſom natural cauſe meane and reaſon) I can not ſée, howe olde age either lacketh or is deſtitute of ſenſe and féeling, no not in theſe kindes of pleaſures, which ſerue for the palate &amp; toth, which we before declared. The ſupe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rioritie, which the chife ruler of the feaſt hath aboue others, by an order whyche our aunceſtours inſtituted, doth greatly contente and pleaſe my mynde: and the merie pleaſaunte queſtions or Caſes, whiche he by an olde lawdable cuſtome
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22986:41"/>proponeth to the compagnie to be diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon, and reaſoned at the table, and the Cuppes of drinke not ebriouſly ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but moderatlye taſted, beinge alſo ſo cleane rinſed and waſſhed, that the cleare droppes of pure water ſtand and cleaue to the ſides, as it wer the ſwete droppes of holeſome dewe, much like to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potation and feaſte whereof <hi>Xenophon</hi> wryteth: and a place to coole our wearie membres in the heate of Sommer, and in the ſturdy and nipping cold of winter, eyther the warme Sunne, or els a good fyer, is vnto me a ſinguler contentation. Theſe orders and dietes am I wonte to obſerue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſeiourne in my Manours and houſes of <hi>Sabinum,</hi> and euery daye I ſe my table furniſhed with the apoincted numbre of my neyghbours neare adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and with talking of diuers matters we prolonge and continewe oure ſupper ſometimes till it be farre in the nighte, euery man layinge in for himſelfe ſuche reaſons and argumentes as hee hath for
<pb facs="tcp:22986:42"/>the corroboration and confirmation of his cauſe and aſſertion.<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiecti∣on </seg>
                  </label> But there is not in old men ſo great a deſire of Carnali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie nor ſuche ticklinge concupiſcence of venerie. I beléeue it well: and it is not onelye frée, from the aſſaultes and pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king luſt therof, but alſo from any deſire or delite at al therunto. For nothinge is gréeuous or heauilie taken of a man, if he neither care nor deſire the ſame. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles</hi> being an aged man, was aſked of one, whether hee gaue himſelfe to anye venerous daliaunce and coiture? Vnto whom he aunſwered &amp; ſaid: god forbidde that I in this age ſhould geue my ſelf to ſuch wanton luſtes, for I haue willingly renounced and fledde awaye frome that kinde of laſciuiouſnes, as from a thinge whiche I know to be like to a Lordlye &amp; imperious maiſter, both beaſtly, ſauage, and furions. But to theym that are deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous therof, it is a greate griefe to lacke and be wythout it: but to theym whyche haue ſatyſfyed theyr naturall luſtes,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22986:42"/>whoſe age fitte for ſuch wantonneſſe is alreadye expired, it is more pleaſure to lack then to vſe it. Albeit he that forceth not for it, can not be ſaid to lacke it, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore not to care for it (I ſay) is more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then to haue ful fruition and ſacie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of it. Now wheras adoleſcencye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth more in theſe pleaſures, the cauſe is becauſe it is more willinge and procliue to folow the things whyche are of ſmall moment and importaunce, as it is of it ſelfe raſhe and wauering: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde ſuche thinges as olde age is delighted and geuen to, the whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe it doe not fully enioye, yet doth it not altogether lacke. Euen as hee that ſitteth on the chyefeſte benche in a Theatre or Liſtes where playes and Enterludes are exhibited, is more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyted to ſée the excellent geſture of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biuius Turpio,</hi> and his incomparable dexteritye in the expreſſe imitation and geſture of anye perſonne, yet hee that ſtandeth a farreof, lookynge ouer other
<pb facs="tcp:22986:43"/>mens ſhoulders hathe ſome delectation aſwell as the others: ſo like wiſe youth and adoleſcencie being by reaſon of their freſhe age, more prone to pleaſures than old age is, hauing and daylye ſéeing the allurements therof more neere to them, is perhappes more frolicke: but old age ſéeing them a loofe and a farre of, is ther in delited as much as is requiſite and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. But what a ſinguler commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is this, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind like an old worne Souldioure is by the meanes of old age raunſomed and exempted from the vglie ſeruitude and thraledome of ſenſualitie, voluptuouſnes, ambition, ſtryfe, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, quarelling, ennemitie, and finallie from al lothſome and fylthy affections, and in ſteede thereof to embrace medio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critie and moderacion, and to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and to liue (as the old ſaying is) with him ſelfe? But if it be furniſſhed withe ſtudie and learning, (which are as it wer the nutriture and ſuſtentacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of old age) truly nothinge is more pleaſaunt then it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22986:43"/>is, being diſmiſſed from all troubleſome entermedlinge with publique affaires &amp; wholly addict to quiet contemptation.<note place="margin">Old men ſtudious.</note> We ſaw <hi>C, Gallus</hi> the famous Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and greate friende to thy father O <hi>Scipio,</hi> ſo intentiuelye addicted to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions aſwel of heauen as of earthe, that he ſéemed to haue none other delite, neither to haue any reſpect at al, for any other worldly buſines. How many nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes did he beſtow vpon ſtudie of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, and neuer ſlepte? How often hath the next morowe appered ere he had left his lucubrations, which he had begonne ouer night? How often did nighte come vpon him, when he had inceſſauntly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured in his Calculations Aſtronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call all daye before, withoute meate or drinke? What a ſinguler pleaſure was it to him, long beforehand to prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and forſhewe the Eclipſes boothe of the Sunne and Moone? what painful laboures ſuſtayned he in the ſtudie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters not of ſo greate momente
<pb facs="tcp:22986:44"/>and importannce as theſe other, but yet verye ſubtile, quicke and wittie? Howe greatlye reioyced <hi>Naeuius</hi> in his comedye whych he entituled the <hi>Punique vvarre?</hi> Howe did <hi>Plautus</hi> in hys Comedye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Truculentus</hi> in manner leape &amp; try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe for ioye? wythe what gladnes was hee ſurpryſed wythal, whenne bee hadde wrytten an other comodye named <hi>Pſeudolus?</hi> I ſaw <hi>Liuius,</hi> who hauynge ſet foorth an Enterlude ſeuen yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I was borne, when <hi>Cethegus</hi> and <hi>Tuditanus</hi> weare Conſuls, lyued and flouriſhed tyll I was a bigge ſtripling. What ſhoulde I ſpeake of the worthye and expert Lawyer <hi>P. Licinius Craſſus,</hi> and of his wouderful knowledge bothe in the Canon and in the Ciuile Lawe? or of the induſtrious contemplation and dyligence of this our <hi>P. Scipio,</hi> who was of late created high Prieſt? And all theſe whome I haue heere named, wee haue ſéene being old men to géeue theymſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to ſtudye. But as for <hi>M. Cethegus,</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:22986:44"/>whom <hi>Ennius</hi> doth very proprely cal the verye pythe and marowe of <hi>Suada</hi> the Goddeſſe of eloquence and pleaſaunte ſpeache, how ſtudiouſly dyd we ſee hym, bente to the arte of Rheiorike &amp; Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in his olde age? what pleaſures ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of banquetyng, of playes, or of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelles and Curtiſans are comporable to theſe vertuous and lawdable pleaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res? Theſe are the ſtudyes of doctrine and learnynge, whyche in men of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and good inclynation, doe growe and increaſe, euen as they theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues doe in age accordyng to that golden ſayinge of <hi>Solon,</hi> who in a briefe pooſye or ſentence ſayd (as we before haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) that hee waxed euerye daye olde,<note place="margin">The ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of wiſe <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi>
                  </note> by learnynge daylye ſome knowledge whereof he was before ignoraunt: then whych pleaſure of mynd, there can none bee greater, none more vertuous, none more commendable. I will now ſpeake of the goodlye pleaſures, whyche Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen haue, wherin I my ſelfe haue
<pb facs="tcp:22986:45"/>great delighte, whiche are not hindered by old age,<note place="margin">I Inſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye.</note> and in my opinion their lyfe is moſt like to a bleſſed and happie mans life. For their traphique and trade of marchandiſe is with the earthe, whyche neuer refuſeth to be vnder their rule and ſubiection, neuer is ſo diſobediente nor obſtinate, but obedient and ſeruiciable, and repayeth with great increaſe of vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (as who would ſaye for the vſe &amp; lone of their ſéedes and toyle) that which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, but at ſometime it doth not ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre ſo much as it doth at an other time, albeit for the moſt part, it requireth their trauailes with a greate ſurpluſage and acceſſe of gaine. But yet, I doe not onely take pleaſure, in the fruictes and grains which it yeldeth, but alſo in the ſtrength, nature and power of the earthe it ſelfe, which receyuing the ſéede in her lappe, and beinge by tillage and good huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie plowed, mollified and well manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, doth for a time at the firſt kéepe and nouriſhe it, beinge couered within it by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22986:45"/>harrowing, which is therfore called <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio,</hi> then doth it make it to appeare and péepe oute of the ground, throughe the warmth which it receiueth by the vapou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous humyditye, and amicable heate, and ſo cheariſſheth it, that in time it bringeth forth a gréene ſtalke lyke at the firſte to graſſe or herbes, the which being ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by the ſmal ſhootes and ſtringes that growe out of the roote, doth by lytle and litle growe vp to a bigge ſtemme, &amp; ſtanding vpright vpon a knottye ſtraw full of ioyntes, (when it nowe waxeth &amp; draweth nere to ripenes) is included in pods or huſkes. Out of the which, as out of a ſheath or hoſe, there commeth forth corne or graine, whiche lay in the eare fenſed, fortifyed and armed againſte the pecking and eating of ſmall byrdes with a Rampier or wal of the awnes or bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. What ſhoulde I recite and declare the plantinge and pruning of vynes, the increaſing and proffites of them? I can not ſufficiently tell you, what incredible
<pb facs="tcp:22986:46"/>ioye and pleaſure I take therin, how my mynde is ſet therein, and this I ſaye, to thentent, that you may throughly vnder ſtande the quietneſſe and recreation of myne old age. I omitte to ſpeake of the vertues of al ſuch thinges as the earthe bringeth forth: how of one ſmal kernell of a figge, or one lytle corne or graine of a grape, and finally of other lytle ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of all other fruictes graynes and yonge ſhootes it bringeth forth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>createth ſuch greate boles and mightye bodyes, and in frucites or herbes ſuche hyghe ſtemmes. The ſmal twigges that bee cut of from the vynes to bee planted els wher, the yonge ympes and griftes, the ſuperfluous braunches that are pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the plantable vynes, the vaulted and arched herbours that are made for pleaſaunte walkes, whereon the vynes maye renue and ſpread abroade and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhe men wythe their coole vmbrage, the euttynge downe of olde vynes, that yonge ſlyppes may theron be ſet, woulde
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22986:46"/>not all theſe allure a manne to loue and haue theym in admiration? The vine is naturally ſtowping and fallyng downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and if it be not with ſhoores and forkes vnderpropped, it groweth toward the grounde: but the ſame by the helpe and furtheraunce of hys tendrelles, whych are to it in ſteede and lieu of han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, raiſeth vp it ſelfe, catcheth, and lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth it ſelfe faſt, to what ſoeuer it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neare, the which in contynuaunce of time wandring and rouing at randon vncomptrolled, and entangling it ſelfe with many other parts, at length the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant care and diligent hand of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman doth by pruning reſtraine, and with his vine hookes ſo cutteth &amp; kepeth vnder, that it can not grow to luxuriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor wieldlye, neither be ouer growen with ſuperfluous braunches, &amp; ſpread out to farre on euerye ſide with buſſhie rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedneſſe. And therfore in the beginning of the Springe tyme, ther commeth oute a younge bourgen or budde in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:22986:47"/>twigges that remayned after the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which do as it were grow oute at the very ioyntes, where thoſe ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous braunches were lopped and cut of: out of which burgeins, the Cluſter doth procéede and appeare, which takinge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and growinge in bigneſſe, what with the bumyditie &amp; iuyce of the earth, and what with the warmth and heate of the ſunne, is for a while at the firſte ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and vitter in taſte, but whenne it is rype and mature, it is bothe ſweete, and tothſome, and being couered and cladde wyth leaues, it receyueth thereby ſuche comforte and helpe, that it neyther lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth expedient and needefull heate, and alſo defendeth it ſelfe from the parching and ardent beames of the Sunne. Now, what can be either for profit more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, or for the ſight and delyting of the eye more gorgious and beautiful, then theſe afore named pleaſures? Whoſe profitable vſe, and gainful poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth not only (as I ſaid before) meruailouſly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22986:47"/>content and pleaſe me, but alſo the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuring, the digging, and the proper na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture therof, is vnto mée pleaſure incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible. The order of the ſtayes or ſhores, wherby the vines are vnderpropped, the tyinge and plattinge of theym together wherby men haue a pleaſaunt and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die galerie to walke in, the byndinge of theym downe, their increaſe and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge abroad, the prunyng of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous braunches, and the new graffing of others in their places (which I ſpoke of) repleniſhe my heart with ioy vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keable: To what purpoſe ſhould I here rehearſe the watringe and irrigation of the plantes, the trenches and deluing of the grounde, the repaſtination or newe digging aboute the rootes, whereby the grounde is made much more fartile and ranke? whereto ſhoulde I ſpeake of the profitte that commeth by dunginge the ground? wherof I haue at large ſpoken in my booke entituled <hi>Of Huſbandrie:</hi> al be it the aunciente and learned Poete
<pb facs="tcp:22986:48"/>
                  <hi>Heſiodus</hi> ſpeaketh neuer a word therof, in his woorke of <hi>Tyllage</hi> and <hi>Ruſticall affaires.</hi> But <hi>Homere</hi> who (as farre as I can gather) was long before <hi>Heſiodus</hi>) in troduceth and bringeth in olde <hi>Laertes,</hi> (ſore longing and languiſſhinge for the abſence of his ſonne <hi>Vlyſses</hi>) after the maner of a huſbandmanne, tyllinge and dunginge his grounde. And the trade of Huſbandrye is not onely pleaſaunt and plentiful, enriched and ſtored with corne, graine, Meadowes, Vineyeardes, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeardes, groues and other places where Trées growe: but alſo with Orchardes, Gardeins, féedyng of Cattal, Swarmes of Bées, and variety of al kynd of ſwete flowers. And not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordrely ſettyng and ſtanding of the Trées and plantes. delite and pleaſe the eyeof the beholder, but alſo the Inſitions and graffinge of younge Slyppes in an other trée: which poinctes and feactes are as wittye and ſubtyle, as anye are in Huſbandrye. Manye oblectamentes of Huſbandmen
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22986:48"/>could I declare, but I wel perceiue, that in theſe few commodities whych I haue already tolde, I haue bene to prolixe and tedious. But you ſhal of youre courteſye beare with my feruent zeale, and pardon my earneſte proſccution of my reaſons and argumentes therin. For, the greate good wil and loue, which I haue and ſtil do beare to Huſbandrye, hathe enforced mee to ſpeake and wade further in it, thenne at the firſte I purpoſed: and alſo Olde age is reported to bée by nature talkatiue and géeuen to loquacitie, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I wyll not ſée me to auouche and ſaye that it is cleare and frée from al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vyces and faultes. And therefore the valyaunt and inuincible duke <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Curius,</hi> when he had atchieue manys notable exploytes and glorious vycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes agaynſte the rebellyous foes and Capytall Ennemyes of the Romayne people, and had ſhewed hymſelfe a Mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure of proweſſe and knightelye forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in ſundrye hazardes, after hée had
<pb facs="tcp:22986:49"/>tryumphed ouer the <hi>Samnites</hi> &amp; <hi>Sabines,</hi> and hadde ſubdued the couragious and myghtye <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> kynge of <hi>Epyrotes,</hi> &amp; ſubiugated al his Territories,<note place="margin">Huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie vſed of noble and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ories and dominions by dent of ſweard and ſtroke of battaile, vnto the Romaine nation, liued in hys old age in this kynd of life: whoſe poore manſion as often as I do beholde (for it adioyneth nere vnto my ſermes) I can not but greatlye mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile and bee aſtonned, eyther to ſée the continencie of this noble man, or els the condition &amp; diſcipline that was in thoſe dayes. And when the <hi>Samnites</hi> after their diſcomfiture, came to this <hi>Curius,</hi> offring him great foyſon and ſummes of golde, they founde him in his owne houſe, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge by the fyre, and ſéething Rape roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in an earthen pot or pipkin, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly refuſed al their offers and rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, telling them in flatte woordes, that he thought it not ſo greate honoure and glorye to poſſeſſe gode,<note place="margin">An enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic to bribes &amp; rewards</note> as to beare rule &amp; to be Lord ouer them, whych had gold.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22986:49"/>How could this noble and valiaunt heart otherwiſe chooſe, but leade an olde age moſt pleaſaunte? But I wil take holde where I left, and ſpeake of huſbandmen as I did before, becauſe I take my ſelfe as one of their order and felowſhippe. Senatours, that is to ſaye, ſage and olde gray headed Counſailours, wer in thoſe dayes Huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmen, for as <hi>Lucius Quintiꝰ Cineinnatus</hi> was holdinge the ploughe &amp; earneſtlye toylinge in his tillage in the fyelde, newes were brought to him that he was elected <hi>Dictator:</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hearing wherof he ſtraight waies left his plough and came to Rome, and was enſtalled in the ſame office of <hi>Dictator</hi> or hyghe mayſter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, executing the ſame withe all ſingleneſſe and ſynceritie, by whoſe commaundement, his vicegerent or Lieutenaunte <hi>Caius Seruilius Hala,</hi> Captayne of the Horſemen, ſlewe <hi>Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Melius</hi> a miſerable and ambitious man, traiterouſlye aſpiting to be kyng. Oute of their fermes and countrie hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:50"/>
                  <hi>Curius,</hi> and manye other old menne were chooſen into the honourable ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and orders of Senaours: whervpon, the officers, or Purſeuauntes whiche ſommoned and called theym to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate were named Currours Poſtes, or ſpecyall Meſſengers. Was therfore the old age of theſe men miſerable, whiche refreſſhed and ſolaced theym ſelues in tillage and Huſbandry? Certes, in mine opynion, I iudge that there can bee no life more bleſſed and fortunate thenne thys is, and not onelye for the honeſte exerciſe and néedeful commoditie which thereby to al mankinde redoundeth (for if Tillage were neglected al the ſorte of vs woulde bewayle the lacke and féele the ſmarte thereof) but alſo becauſe of the delectation (as is before ſayde) and the plentyfulues or aboundaunce of all thinges, whiche eyther to the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manne, his foode and nutriment, or els to the worſhippe and adoration of the goddes are requyſitie and conuena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22986:50"/>And becauſe manye doe wiſhe and deſire this, let vs reconcile our ſelues, &amp; make a firme peace &amp; infringible atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente with Pleaſure. For euery good and ſubſtantiall houſeholder hathe euer his Sellers for wyne and oyle, and other offices for prouiſion of houſehold reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſhed and well ſtored, yea his whole houſe is with al néedeful vtenſiles in al poincts furniſſhed, it is neither deſtitute of Hogge, Kidde, Lambe, poultrie ware, Mylke, Chéeſe nor hony. Now huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men them ſelues, find their Gardeine ſo commodious vnto them, (becauſe it my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth and bringeth foorthe plentye of good herbes, wherwith they make them Saleties and lyue well contented with their golden mediocritye, and becauſe it was euer readye at hande and needed no fyre to dreeſſe and ſéethe theym) that they called it an other Larder or fleſhe ſhambles:<note place="margin">Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> altera ſuccidia.</note> alſo theſe ſame gardeine her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes being their daily foode and ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are by hunting and hawking made
<pb facs="tcp:22986:51"/>more pleaſant and tothſome, althoughe theſe be exerciſes, which do not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily belong to Huſbandrie, but are rather ſuperuacuous and vaine. What maye I now ſay of the gréene verdure and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hewe of the ſwéete Meadowes, or the ordrely ſetting of Trées, or of the fourme and beautye of vines, and places beſette with direct rowes of Oliue Trées? I wil in few words ſhew, what I think herein. Ther can nothing be either for vſe more commodious, or for profitte more gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or for the gazing view of the gréedie eye more trymme and elegante, then a wel tilled and manured fielde, from the fruition of whych ſo great and bleſſed a thinge, Old age bringeth vnto man not onely no hindraunce nor impedimente, but rather inuiteth &amp; allureth him vnto it. For wher may old age be ſo wel warmed either by breathing and ſitting againſte the hoate ſunne, or by a good fier: or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywyſe, as the time and ſeaſon of the yeare ferueth, bee ſo holeſomlye cooled
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22986:51"/>in ſhadye places, or be ſo aptlye bayned as in the countraye? Let vs therfore bid adieu to al ſuch youthly prankes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, as luſtye and gréene headed Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantes agitated and pricked wythe the feruent heate of vnaduiſed adoleſcencye, do envre them ſelues withal, god ſpéede them wel with their vſual diſportes and daliaunce, let them take to theymſelues their armoure, weapons, and Artillerie, let vs permit and géeue them good leaue to daunte fierce Horſes, and with ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res in reſt to mount on couragious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, let theym handle the pike, toſſe the Iaueline and Clubbe dayly, and play at the Tenyſe, exerciſe theym ſelues with runnynge, Swymminge, and ſuche like déedes of actiuitie and nymbleneſſe: to vs olde men amonge all their other games and paſtimes, lette theym leaue the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, the Chaunce bone or dyce, and the Cheſſe, whiche without any daunger or ſore ſtrayning of the body maye be prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed: and yet I wil not ſéeme to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>owe
<pb facs="tcp:22986:52"/>theſe laſte named games, further then euery man himſelfe is diſpoſed, becauſe they be not neceſſarie, and old age maye without theym be bleſſed and fortunate. The bookes of <hi>Xenophon</hi> are very expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and profitable for many purpoſes, the which I would wiſhe, that you ſhold read ouer and pervſe dyligentlye, as you do. How copiouſly doth he extol &amp; praiſe huſbandry in his booke which he wrate of the right ordering and domeſtical pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for houſeholde? And becauſe you ſhal wel vnderſtand, that he thinketh no thinge more princelyke then the maner of Tillage and Huſbandry, he entrodu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Socrates</hi> in that booke reaſoninge with <hi>Critobulus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Kinge <hi>Cyrus</hi> much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrye.</note> and tellyng him, howe the noble and puiſſaunt <hi>Cyrus</hi> the ſecond of that name, kinge of <hi>Perſia,</hi> (a Prince not onelye conſpicuous and renowmed for his incomparable witte and pollicye, but alſo ſuch a one as had the regiment and ſoueraignetie ouer manye greate Realmes, &amp; populous countreys) deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22986:52"/>excetingly therin. For when as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a certain time a noble man of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traie.<note place="margin">Lyſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> 
                  <hi>Lacedemonia,</hi> called <hi>Lyſander</hi> came vnto him, then ſeiourning at his faire ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Sardis</hi> &amp; broughte to him from hys felowes in armes &amp; confederates, diuers rich and honorable preſents, he not only in moſt amicable wiſe receiued &amp; welco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him, ſhewing to him al poinctes of princely courteſie in al other things ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallye, but namelye in that, he ſhewed him a certain goodly field, hedged in and trimelye encloſed, ſet full of trées of all ſorts, moſt exquiſitely planted. Whiche when <hi>Lyſander</hi> had well viewed, &amp; ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly a good while with an admiracion beheld, &amp; had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered both the height of the Trées, &amp; the exacte order which was preciſely obſerued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> placing &amp; ſetting of them ſo equidiſtantly, that which way ſo euer a man caſt his eyes they ſtoode in a moſt perfect fourme of a Quincu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, the ground ſo wel laboured &amp; ſo pure of it ſelf withal, &amp; the redolent ſmelles which the
<pb facs="tcp:22986:53"/>ſwéete floures yelded: he ſpake vnto the king and ſaide: that he did not ſo muche muſe &amp; meruayle at the diligence, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlyng and fine workemanſhippe, as he did at the promptitude of wit, the ſubtile arte, and the politike conuaighaunce of him that planted and ſet theym in ſuche perfecte meaſure and proporcion. Vnto whom <hi>Cyrus</hi> made this aunſwere: It is euen I (O <hi>Lyſander</hi>) and none other man, that haue made and by meaſure planted all theſe trées which thou ſéeſt, the order of the rowes wherein they ſtand, is my only deuyſe, this platte and deſeription I my ſelfe drew, and a great meignye of theſe trées wer graffed and planted with the labour of myne owne handes. Then <hi>Lyſander</hi> firing his eyes vpon the kings purple Robes and his riche attire, well noting the propre feacture of his comely bodye, the beautifull lineamentes and Symmetrie of his wel and portely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacte perſonage, together withe all the coſtlye apparaile wherein hee was after
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22986:53"/>the <hi>Perſian</hi> maner arayed, his garments powdred and fringed with much golde, precious ſtones, &amp; Orient pearles whoſe value was ineſtimable, ſpake theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnto him: Truly O <hi>Cyrus</hi> nowe doe I wel ſe, that it is not done without right good cauſe and conſideracion, that thou art bruyted abroad and reported in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place to bee a happie and a fortunate Prynce,<note place="margin">Virtuti fortuna comes.</note> for vnto thy rare vertue and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, fortune alſo is conioyned and aſſociated. Therefore old men maye vſe and enioye this fortune, neither is their age any ſuch lette or obſtacle for theym, but that they may in al other thinges do ſemblablye, but moſt chiefly let vs em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the huſbandmans life, and employ our ſelues to manure and til the ground euen vntyl the extreme and laſt point of our age. We haue hearde ſaye, that <hi>M. Valerius Coruinus</hi> liued tyll hee was an hundreth yeres old, and in the latter end of his old age, lyued in the Countraye, &amp; gaue himſelfe to culture and huſbandry,
<pb facs="tcp:22986:54"/>after he had bene ſixe times Conſul, and betwéene his firſt and his ſixte Couſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late there were xlvi yeares. Therefore that ſpace and time of yeares which our forefathers apointed and ment to be the beginning of old age, he ſo vigorouſlye ſuſtayned and ouercame, that hee was thought worthye to beare the higheſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and dygnityes in the Communs wealthe. And his extreme olde age was hearein more fortunate and bleſſed then hys myddle age, becauſe it was decora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a great deale more honour and authorytie, and put to much leſſe paines and laboure. Nowe the higheſte title of prayſe that can be geuen to olde age is Authorytie. O what a noble magyſtrate was <hi>L. Cecilius Metellus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the greateſte oruame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of old age</note> what a worthie authoritie was there in <hi>Attilius Collati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> in whoſe prayſe and commendacion many nacions with one voice &amp; conſent gaue this honourable ſtile, to be called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble protectoure, the ſure Shielde, the truſty leanyng ſtaffe, and the ſtrong bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaux
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22986:54"/>of the Romaine people and their libertyes. The Epitaphe or Encomye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was engrauen vpon his Tombe is wel knowen. Worthily therfore and by good right oughte he to be ſurnamed a graue honourable perſonage, of whom ſo good a report and fame, was generally blazed and teſtified by the mouthe of ſo manye men, withoute diſdaigne, enuye, heart-burning, or grudging of any. What a Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel had we of late dayes of <hi>P. Craſſus</hi> when he was high prieſt? or of <hi>M. Lepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> who in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame office ſucceded him? wherto ſhold I ſpeake of <hi>Paulus Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> or <hi>Africanus</hi> or of <hi>Quintus Maximus</hi> (of whom I ſpake a lytle before) in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there was ſuche a portelye grace and Maieſtye, that not onelye in their wyſe and dyſcréete Counſayles, but alſo in theyr vyſages &amp; lookes, yea and in their beckes there was euidentlye to be ſeene and deſcryed the true and lyuely Image of perfecte Aucthorytie? Olde age and ſpecyallye ſuche as is not contempned
<pb facs="tcp:22986:55"/>nor deryded, but reuerenced and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hath in it ſo greate aucthoritye, that it is muche more to bee eſteemed and is farre moore woorthe, then all the vaine pleaſures of headye and raſhe Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencye.<note place="margin">What maner of olde age is to be Prayſed.</note> But this I woulde require you to remembre, that in all this my talke, I doe prayſe that olde age, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion was layed and grounded in the yeares of youthe, and toke his firſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at Adoleſcencie. Whervpon my old ſayinge (which in open audience I haue ſo often vſed to ſpeake, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto al men with one accord conſented) is verifyed, which was, that that old age which had no noble déedes to defende it ſelfe withal, but leaned onely to vaine iangling words &amp; prating vauntes, was wretched &amp; miſerable. It is not the hoare head, and wrinkled face which by and by bringeth honour and purchaſeth eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but it is an honeſte and godlye life that hath euer bene conuerſaunte and trayned in vertue which getteth dignity
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22986:55"/>and high aucthority in the end. For theſe things which ſéeme to be verie ſmal, are in déede very honourable: to be ſaluted, &amp; deſired into the compaignie of honeſte men, to ſée manye men to goe aſyde and géeue the way where they ſhal paſſe, to be reuerenced, to be broughte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted home, to haue many wayters ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing attendaunce on theym, when they goe from home, to be ſued vnto for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, and to be requeſted for their patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage &amp; aduiſe in waighty and difficulte matters, whyche thinges bothe amonge vs and in al other wel gouerned and cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile ordered Cities are moſt diligentlye and preciſely obſerued <hi>Lyſander</hi> a prince of <hi>Lacedemonia:</hi> (of whome I ſpake ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while) is reported, that he woulde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſay, that the moſt honeſte and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Manſion or Lodginge for old age to dwel and liue in, was in <hi>Lacedemonia:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Great re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerence among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Heathen ſhewed to olde age.</note> for in no place els is ſo muche preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and reuerence ſhewed and géeuen to old age as ther, It is alſo conſecrated
<pb facs="tcp:22986:56"/>to perpetual memorye and left in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that a certain elderly man came on a time into the Theatre at <hi>Athens</hi> wher ſolemne Playes and pageauntes where exhibited to the people, where ther was not one man in the whole aſſemblye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his natural countrye men and felow Citeſins that ſhewed to him anye cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie neither gaue to him anye roume to ſitte in and repooſe his weake and debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litated membres: but when hee came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> (who as it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced were at that tyme ther as Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours and had their places in reſpect of their Ambaſſade accordinglye apoincted them) they al arooſe &amp; place to him, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and receyuyng hym among them to ſit in the eaſieſt &amp; honourableſt ſeate. At which curteous vrbanitie of the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians,</hi> when al the people in token of praiſe clapped their hands with many ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s gratulatory, one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours brake out in theſe words &amp; ſayd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Athenians</hi> knew wel what was honeſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22986:56"/>&amp; vertuous, but to do it they would not. Many good orders are in our conſiſtorye or Colledge of Senatours, &amp; namely this is one: for euery one according to his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioritie and elderſhyp in yeres, doth firſt pronounce his ſentence and vtter hys mynd. And the auncient and aged <hi>Augurs</hi> are eſtéemed and preferred not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore right honourable maieſtrats which beare rule &amp; office, but alſo before them, that haue the chiefe regiment and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne rule in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what corporal pleaſures are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with theſe rewards and aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of authority? wherein whoſoeuer gloriouſlye haue behaued theymſelues, they in mine opynion haue moſt worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; comendably played the pageaunte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole diſcourſe of their age,<note place="margin">Theſe are the vices of maners &amp; not of old age.</note> &amp; not like dranelike &amp; idle ſtage players in the laſt act of al, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer &amp; quailed. But many old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be waiward, il to pleaſe, lowring, comberous, fretting &amp; chafing, whining &amp; in exporable, and (if we throughly ſifte
<pb facs="tcp:22986:57"/>out the matter) myſerable nygardes and penchpentes alſo: but al theſe are not the faultes peculier to old age, but incident to them whoſe naughty maners be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect &amp; diſpoſed therunto. But their way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes and other faultes (which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearced) may alledge and pretend a ſmall pretext of excuſation, whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe it be not true, yet it is ſuch as in apparaunce ſéemeth to be probable. For they thinke theymſelues to bee contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, flowted, vnregarded and deryded.</p>
               <p>Furthermore in a weake &amp; ſore worne body. (ſuch as old men haue) euery ſmal offence is odious and ſéemeth to theym diſpleaſunt: al which faultes neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe through good maners and diſcipline are condulcate, qualefied &amp; made ſwete, which thing to be true, may wel be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued bothe by the common courſe of mens lyuing, and alſo by the Comedy of <hi>Terence</hi> entytuled <hi>Adelphi,</hi> where he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth two brethren of contrarye diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, inclinacion and maners, and the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22986:57"/>one his nature in all poinctes varyinge and ſwaruinge from the others. What ruſtical behauioure and cloyniſhe blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is in the one? Againe, what courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vrbanitie, what honeſt demeanoure, what ciuil faſſhions, what affability and what lenitie is in the other? So ſtandeth the matter, and ſo by dayly experience is it to be ſene. For euen as euery wyne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old and ſtanding long is not conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into vineigre: ſo likewiſe is not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age, ſower, eigre and vnpleaſaunt.<note place="margin">Meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie all owa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in an old man.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity and ſterneneſſe in old age I well allow and commend, ſo that a moderate meane therin (as in al other thinges) be obſerued, but bitterneſſe and rigorous dealinge I can in no wyſe brooke nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way withall.<note place="margin">Nothing ſtandeth more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte reaſon, then for an old ma to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uctous.</note> But as for the avarice and couetouſnes of old menne, I am not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therwith, neither doe I knowe what it meaneth. For what can be more abſurde or repugnaunt to al reaſon, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a wayfaring man when his iourney is now almoſt diſpatched and brought to
<pb facs="tcp:22986:58"/>an ende and hath but litle way to goe, to prouyde and furniſhe him ſelfe with the more victualles, and the ſhorter that his iourneye is, the more to ſéeke and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueigh for coſtage?</p>
               <p>The fourth cauſe, whyche moſte of all greueth &amp; diſquieteth old men, remaineth yet behind vndiſcuſſed, which is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching of death, &amp; the néereneſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which truly can not be farre of frome olde age. O miſerable and wretched olde caitife, if in ſee longe a time as hee hath lyued, hée hathe not perceaued and learned, that deathe is vtterlye to bee contemned and not at all to bee feared:<note place="margin">Deathe not to bee feared.</note> whiche were either flatlye to bee deſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed if it didde vtterlye kyll and ſlea the mynde, that nothinge afterward ſhoulde remayne: or els is greatlye to be deſyred if it bée the inſtrumente and gate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſame mynde or ſoule paſſeth and is caryed into blyſſe, for euermore wyth immortall and euerlaſtynge felycitye to bee eternized. Certes there canne no
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22986:58"/>no thirde or meane be founde. Therfore what ſhould I feare, if after death I ſhal bee eyther not myſerable, or els bleſſed? notwithſt andynge who is hée that hath ſoe ſmall reaſon and wytte, to auouche and awarraunt hymſelfe (althoughe hee were neuer ſo luſtie) that he ſhall lyue tyl the nexte eueninge?<note place="margin">Youth more ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iecte to ſickeneſſe then age.</note> Yea I ſay this further, younge menne are ſubiecte to moe occaſyons of deathe, (becauſe of the humours and bloude which do abounde in theym, and are the nouriſſhers of the matter of Maladyes and dyſeaſes. They fall ſooner into ſickeneſſe, and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, their dyſeaſes are more peryllous and vehemente, theyr recouerye and cure more dyfficile. And therefore there are but féewe that lyue tyll they come to Olde age, whyche if it weare not ſo, but that there myght be a great number of old menne, they woulde liue a greate deale more pleaſauntlye and wyſely.</p>
               <p>For wytte, reaſon and good counſayle reſteth in olde menne, and therefore if
<pb facs="tcp:22986:59"/>there were no olde men,<note place="margin">Comon weelthes and cities beſie go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> there woulde conſequently bee no Cityes. But I will leaue theſe digreſſions or byreckenings, and conuert my talke to ſpeake of immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent death. Is this any euil or fault that can be laied to old age, ſithens you dayly ſée the ſame to belong and be commune aſwell to Adoleſcencie?<note place="margin">Deathe ſparethe no age.</note> I my ſelfe haue had good proofe and felt the heauy expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, not only by the immature deathe of my worthy and louing Sonne, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of thy brethren, <hi>Scipio,</hi> (of whome the Romaines for their noble towardneſſe, had conceyued a great hope to ſee theim aduaunced to moſt ample and high dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes) that death is common to all age, both young and old indifferently. But a younge man hopeth to liue long, which an old man may not looke to do. He tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye féedeth him ſelfe with a vaine and a fooliſhe hope. For what méerer folly can there be, thenne to accompte and repute things which be doubtful &amp; vncertaine, for infallible and certaine, and thinges
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22986:59"/>that are falſe, for true? An old man hath nothing to hope for: but he is therfore in farre better ſtate and caſe,<note place="margin">The olde man is in better ſtate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the yong man is.</note> then is a yong man, for he hath already enioyed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned that, whych the younge man doth but hope for. The one deſireth to lyue long, the other hath already liued long: albeit (O Lorde) what is in mans life, that may be ſayd to be long and of anye diuturnitye. Admitte we liue til extreme old age: let vs hope and thinke that wée ſhal lyue as long as euer dyd the king of <hi>Tarteſsians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Argan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> lyued. <hi>120.</hi> ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeares.</note> His name (as I find in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes) was <hi>Argantonius,</hi> who in the Iſles called <hi>Gades</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furtheſt parts of <hi>Spaine</hi> rayned lxxx. yeares and liued a hundreth and twentye. But to me there ſeemeth nothing long, wherein anye extréeme or end is: for when that ende or extreme is once come, then al which is already paſt, is quight gone, and nothing remayneth but onely that which a man hath by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue atchieued, and by good déedes &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes perpetrated. For houres goe awaye
<pb facs="tcp:22986:60"/>apace, ſo doe dayees, monethes and yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and the tyme whiche is once ſlipte by, and gone, neuer retourneth, neyther can the tymes and things whych are to come, be preciſelye knowen. Therefore euerye one ought to be contented wyth the ſpace &amp; tyme, whych god graunteth him to liue. For he that is a Stageplaier néedeth not of neceſſitye to bee an Actor in the Enterlude or Comody tyl the laſt end thereof, (to delyghte the beholders) but in what acte of the ſame ſo euer hée playeth or chaunceth to bée, he muſte ſo expreſſelye handle and playe his parte, that hée maye wynne prayſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion: neyther ſhoulde a wyſeman liue tyll the <hi>Plaudite</hi> be ſtryken vp. For a ſhorte ſpace and tyme of lyfe, is longe ynoughe to lyue well and honeſtly, and in whatſoeuer age we bee in, it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficyente to haue lyued therein godlye and vertuouſlye. But if you procéede further, and lyue to extremytye of age, you muſte not bée diſcontented nor ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeued
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22986:60"/>ther with, no more thenne Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandemen doe, to ſée after a pleaſaunte and temperate Springe ſeaſonne, Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and Autumne to ſuccéede. For the Springe tyme reſembleth and is like to Adoleſcencye, dyſplayinge and playnlye ſhewynge what fruyctes wyll growe: all the other tymes and ſeaſons ſerue to reape, mowe, cutte downe, gather, gleane, and receyue theym into the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">The fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ictes of olde age.</note> Nowe, the fruicte of Olde age (as I ſayde before) is a pure and vpryghte Conſcience, and the good teſtimonye or witneſſe that a mans owne mynde bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, of the vertuous and irrepreh euſible lyfe, decentlye and inculpable ledde.</p>
               <p>For all thinges whiche come by courſe of Nature are to bee reckened and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted among good things: and what is ſooe muche accordynge to naturall courſe, as for an Olde aged manne to dye? Whych doothe happen to younge men, as it were Maugre Natures good wyll. Therefore younge men in myne
<pb facs="tcp:22986:61"/>opynyon ſéeme ſo to dye,<note place="margin">Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gle for bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of paine in dying but olde men die, lyke the going oure of a Candle.</note> as when a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and violente flame of fyre isquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, withe a greate quantytye or effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of water: but old men dye, as it wer, fyer, which lacking woode and combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter to nouriſhe it, goeth out qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly, and is quenched, as though it were of his owne accord, not forciblye. And as Apples which are gréene and vuripe, are not plucked from the Trée but by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine violent plucking, but if they be ripe and mellow, they fal voluntarily downe from the Trée: So lyke wyſe, yongemen depart out of their life by violent force &amp; painful ſtruggelyng, but old men dye by a certayne rypenes and maturitye. And as often as I thinke thereon, I am rapt with ſuch ioy and coumfort, that the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer I draw &amp; approch to death, the ſoner me thinke, I ſée the dry land, &amp; (as it wer after a long Nauigacion and Seafaring voyage) ſhal at length arriue at the quiet hauen and Port of all reſt and ſecuritye. All other ages haue a certayne number
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22986:61"/>of yeares apointed, how long euery one continueth, but vnto old age ther are no determinate and certayne tymes limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and prefixed, and therefore thou ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt ther in well and laudablye, as long as thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt execute thy office, dyſcharge thy dutye, and defend thyne aucthoritye, &amp; yet neuertheleſſe to contempne death. And for this cauſe, it happeneth, that old age is endued with greater courage and animoſitie, then Adoleſlencie and youth is. And this is the cauſe, that when the Tyraunt <hi>Pyliſtratus</hi> demaunded of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> how he durſt be ſo bold, or wherin he repoſed his truſt, ſo wilfully and boldly to again ſay &amp; diſobaie his Procedings: <hi>Solon</hi> Aunſwered him that he truſted to his Old age, and that was it, that made him ful of Courage, and gaue him bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to reſiſt him: for as much as he with lawleſſe force and monſtruons tyranny had attempted to oppreſſe the Common wealth, myſerably fruſſhed through his vnbrydeled and tyrannycall inuaſions.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22986:62"/>
               <p>But the beſte ende of life is this: when nature which compacted and framed the body, doth like wyſe diſſolue and bringe to deathe the ſame, beinge in good and perfecte remembraunce, the vſe of the wittes and ſenſes in no parte appayred nor dimininiſſhed. For euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrighte, whiche made the Shippe, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth beſte howe to vndoe and pulle the ſame aſundre againe, and as none hath better ſkill to vnioynte or take downe a houſe, then the Carpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter that made it: euen ſo nature, which faſſhioned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the body &amp; ſet the ſame in a moſt decent Symmetrie, doth beſte diſſolue &amp; end it by natural death. For euerye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glutinacion when it is freſh and newly glewed together, wil not eaſily be pulled a ſundre but by violent haling and forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rupture, but when it is inueterate &amp; old, it may eaſilye be diuelled &amp; ſeuered. Thus you ſée, that the ſmall remanent and time of oure race and lyfe whyche is behinde vnrunne, is neyther affectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22986:62"/>to be deſired, nor without cauſe to bee lefte and forſaken. And the famous Philoſopher <hi>Pythagoras,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This life is but a warfare.</note> géeueth vs a ſore charge, that we ſhould not departe oute of the garriſon and wardehouſe of this life, vnleſſe we haue commiſſion &amp; commaundement from our general cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whiche is <hi>GOD. Solon</hi> hys wiſe ſaying is verye notable and praiſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye, for hee woulde not that his deathe ſhould be vnbewayled and vnlamented of his friends. His meanyng (I thinke) was, becauſe he would not ſeeme to be forgotten, but rather entierly to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued &amp; remembred of his frends, which thinge their dolourous plaintes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward griefes at his laſt end and funeral obſequies ſhold bewray &amp; euidently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But yet <hi>Ennius</hi> his opinion in like caſe, may in my iudgement be better al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, for he woulde not haue his frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to moane and lamente for him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his deathe, and theſe are hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:22986:63"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Surceaſſe from teares, when I am dead,</l>
                  <l>And let not them for me be ſheadde.</l>
                  <l>VVhen death ſhall with his deadly darte,</l>
                  <l>My Corps and Soule aſundre part.</l>
                  <l>And why? the clanging trumpe of fame</l>
                  <l>Shall euer ſounde abroade my name.</l>
               </q>
               <p>This noble Poete woulde not haue the deathe of theym to be lamented and with feminine blubbering &amp; ſchrietches to be bewayled, whoſe praiſe and vertue is immortalized and enrolled in the boke of fame, &amp; their worthy déedes regiſtred in the ſcroll of eternity. As touching the bitter panges and extreame agonyes whyche they ſuffer that lye in dyinge, (if there may any ſuch be) trulye it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but for a ſmal while, ſpeciallye in an old man: and after death, the ſence is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as is bleſſed and optable, or els it is none at al. But al yong men ought to imprint this in their myndes, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate the ſame, that they be not in anye ſeruyle and daſtardlye feare of death, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22986:63"/>to ſtand at defiaunce and contempne it.<note place="margin">Hee that ſtandethe in feare of death, cannot be quiet in mynd.</note> For whoſoeuer envreth not him ſelfe with this meditation, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not haue a quiet mynd. We are moſt ſure that we muſte dye, &amp; we know not whether oure houre will come euen that ſame verye daye. Therfore he that euerye houre ſtandeth in feare of death,<note place="margin">Nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain then death, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine then the houre of death.</note> how can hys mynd bee in any reſt or tranquilitye. Wher of ther néedeth no very long diſputacion to bée had, ſith I do wel remembre not onelye <hi>L. Brutus,</hi> whoe in the quarrell of his Countrye whyche was deſpoyled and wyth tyrannye oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Valiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te knightes whiche dyed for ſauegard of the countrie.</note> moſt manfully was ſlaine: the two <hi>Decij,</hi> who being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at al pieces &amp; mounted on horſeback galloped and gaue them ſelues willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to death for their Countrie ſake: <hi>M. Regulus,</hi> who (rather then he would for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare him ſelfe, and breake promyſe wyth hys moſt deadly and bloudy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes) went wyllyngly to his moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne torment and puniſhment (wher he wel knew that he ſhould ſuffer death af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:22986:64"/>a ſtraunge and terreble maner) and would not in any wiſe by his kinſfolkes and friends be altered and remoued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his determinacion: The twoe <hi>Scipioes,</hi> who with their owne bodyes choiſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtoppe the paſſage of the freſhe ſuccours (whiche vnder the conducte of <hi>Haſdrubal,</hi> came to ayde <hi>Hanniball</hi> and the proude <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> ſore infeſting &amp; afflicting Italye with ſweard, famine, and fyre) then to ſuffer and permit them, to ſet any foote within the territories &amp; Precinctes of the Romaine dition: your Graundfather <hi>L. Paulus,</hi> who throughe the temeritie and folye of his fellowe in office <hi>Terentius Varro,</hi> was in that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious ouerthrowe and ſhameful dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture, in the conflict and battaile of <hi>Cannas,</hi> ſlaine and brought to confuſion: and <hi>M. Marcellus,</hi> whoſe valiaunce and magnanimitie was ſo great and ſo weil tryed, that his &amp; our moſt cruel ennemye <hi>Hannibal,</hi> when he hadde ſlaine him in the field, cauſed his dead corſe with all
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22986:64"/>funeral pompe and ſolemnitie of ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be enterred: but alſo how our le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions and Armyes, couragiouſly aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to take ſuch voyages, &amp; venturous expeditions into ſuch dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous places, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they loked to retourne aliue again, wherof I haue wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in my booke of <hi>Originalles.</hi> Shal therefore olde men whych haue great knowledge &amp; experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence feare that, which yong ſtriplings &amp; the ſame not only vnſkilful but alſo blu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ruſtical do contemne &amp; care not for? But me thinke, ſocietie of al things, can ſeth ſo ciety of life.<note place="margin">Euerye age hathe his pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier delite &amp; ſtudye.</note> Ther are ſome phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall and childyſhe playes whereat youge children in their childhode delight to playe: ſhal therfore yong men and tall felowes addicte them ſelues to the ſame ſemblablie? There are ſome exerciſes &amp; affections wherein youthly yeares doe envre them ſelues: ſhall the rype &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant age (whych is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myddle age of manne) looke to playe at the ſame? And of this myddle age, there are ſome
<pb facs="tcp:22986:65"/>ſtudyes, willes and appetites, whyche old age careth not for. And ther be ſome ſtudies and exerciſes belonging and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to old age. And therfore as the pleaſure and delite of the ſtudies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes in freſſher and luſtier ages dothe in time were away and come to an end, ſo dothe the ſtudyes of olde age in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuaunce and tract of time alſo dye and vaniſh. And when this pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull contentacions begynne in olde men once to decreaſe, then doth ſacietye of life bring to theym a conuenable and mature tyme to dye. For verily I cannot ſe, why I ſhoulde not be bolde to vtter and declare to you twaine, the verye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier cogitacions of my hart, and the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which I haue of death: and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe I ſuppoſe that I do better knowe and ſée it, as one, that nowe am neere the pittes brinke, hauinge one of my féete already in the graue. And I am in this beléefe (O <hi>P. Scipio</hi> and <hi>C. Laelie</hi>) that your noble fathers, menne for their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22986:65"/>vertuous maners and worthy demerites immortalized, who alſo weare my moſte deare and louing friends, do yet liue, yea and ſuch a life, as is worthye only to bée called a lyfe, which is immortall and not tranſitory. For ſo long as wée dwel and be included within this lumpiſh body pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portioned with ioyntes, ſynewes, fleſhe, bone, and other partes,<note place="margin">The bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is the pryſon or caſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule.</note> whiche maye bee called the pryſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or caſe of our Soule, we are dryuen &amp; by a neceſſitie enforced to do ſome actions (wil we or nill we) as to ſlepe, eate, drinke &amp;c: and to do ſom cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſome workes whiche are ineuitable. But the minde or ſoule which is diuine and celeſtiall, ſent downe from god oute of Heauen and infuſed into man, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and as it were, forciblye deiected or thruſte downe to the earthe, beinge a place quighte contrarie to diuine nature and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternitye, becauſe it is mortall and viſible wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other is immortal &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible.<note place="margin">Note the opinion of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</note> But I do thinke, that the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Gods inſpired myndes into humaine
<pb facs="tcp:22986:66"/>bodyes, becauſe ther ſhould be ſome to inhabite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, who beholdyng &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the orders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> celeſtial bodies, &amp; waighing how duelie they obſerue their courſes and motions, might imitate and folow the ſame right order in the trades of their life and conſtancy. And not only reaſon and frequent diſputacion moueth me thus to beleue, but alſo the profou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de doctrine and authorities of moſt noble &amp; approued Philoſophers. For I haue ben in place, where I harde that <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and his diſciples which inhabiied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our countrey and were in maner frée Denizons within our precincte and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion (for they wer once named <hi>Italian Philoſophers</hi>) affirmed and ſaid, that they weare neuer otherwyſe perſwaded nor neuer helde opinion to the contrarie, but that our mindes were fourmed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from the vniuerſal diuinity of god. Furthermore it was tolde me, what <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> diſputed and ſpake concerning the immortalitye of the ſoule, and what hée
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22986:66"/>openly ſayd beinge an auncient philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and one, whom <hi>Apollo</hi> his Oracle iudged the wiſeſt man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, euen the laſt day of his life, a litle before his death. What néedeth many wordes? I am ſo firmelye perſwaded and on thys poinct ſo whollye reſolued, ſeinge there is ſo great celeritie of the mynde, ſo good remembraunce of thinges paſte, and ſo great forcaſt and prudeuce in thinges to come, ſo many Artes, ſo many Sciences, ſo many inuentions &amp; ingenious deuiſes, that the nature whiche vnderſtandeth &amp; contayneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of al theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gs is not mortal.<note place="margin">The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſoule pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued.</note> And ſith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind is euer moued, hauing no beginning of mocion becauſe it moueth it ſelfe, &amp; ſhall neuer haue any end of mocion, becauſe it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, &amp; ſhal neuer leaue it ſelf: and ſith the nature of the mind is ſimple, hauing nothing mixed to it which is vnlike and diſcrepant to it, I therby know, that it is indiuiſible, wherevpon it conſequentlye followethe, that for as muche as it is
<pb facs="tcp:22986:67"/>diuiſible, it can neuer do &amp; periſh vtterly. And theſe reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s folowing make much for the probacion therof, that men know many thinges before they be borne, that Children (notwithſtanding the abſtruſe and painfull difficultie of Artes) doe ſo quicklye learne and as who would ſaye, ſnatchingly conceiue innumerable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, that they ſéeme, not than at the fyrſt to learne them, but rather repete and cal them againe to memorye. Theſe bee for the moſt parte the argumentes and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which the dyuine philoſopher <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> alledgeth and bringeth for his proufe of the immortalitye of the ſoules. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Xenephon</hi> writethe, that Kinge <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> the elder lyinge on his deathe bedde, ſpake theſe words folowing to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:<note place="margin">Lib. 8. de paed. Cy.</note> I would not (my children) that you ſhould thinke, when I am departed out of this life and goone frome you, that I ſhal be no wher or brought to nothyng. For you neuer ſawe with your bodilye eyes, my mynde, duringe all this whyle
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22986:67"/>that I lyued here with you: but as long as I dwelled in this bodye, you wel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued and knewe by my valyaunte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploytes and actes, that I hadde a minde. Therfore thinke you not otherwiſe, but that I am the very ſame ſtil, and my ſaid mynde ſhall ſtill remayne as before, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe you ſée it not viſiblie. For ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde the noble memoriall and honourable Monumentes of Princes &amp; worthy Perſonages remaine after their death, if in their life time, by the pollicie and proweſſe of their minds, they did not atchieue ſome worthy enterpiſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their fame and honoure might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred and magnifyed of their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Truly it would neuer ſincke in my braine that the minds or ſoules did liue onelye whyle they remayned in mortall bodyes, and beyng departed out of them vtterly to dy, that no more of them ſhold remaine. Nor that the ſoule and mynd of ſottes and fooles is doltiſh and blockiſhe
<pb facs="tcp:22986:68"/>whenne it is ſette at libertye and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted oute of their foolyſhe Bodyes: but whenne it is puryfyed frome the fylthye admixtion and droſſie impurytye of the ſame bodye, and fyned frome imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and beginning to be ſounde, perfect and cleare, thenne is it wyſe, ſapiente and incorrupte.</p>
               <p>And Mannes nature beynge by death diſſolued, it is apparaunte and well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe to all menne knowen, to what place all the other partes doe goe: for they dooe all retourne to that matter, whereof they hadde theyr fyrſt and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryginall beginninge: but the mynd one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye is neuer wythe anye bodylye eyes ſéene nor perceyued, neyther when it is in the Bodye nor whenne it goeth and departeth oute of the bodye.</p>
               <p>Nowe, you ſee that nothinge is ſoe like to deathe as Sleape. And yet the myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of them that are a ſleape do greatly declare their diuinitie: for whenne they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22986:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>be at quietneſſe &amp; reſt &amp; wyth no careful cogitations ouerwhelmed, they doe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſée mannye thinges to come, wheareby it may playnlye be perceyued, howe and in what happy ſtate they ſhall be, when they bee diſmiſſed and diſcharged oute of theyr dungeon or gaole of theyr mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Bodyes. Yf therefore theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges bée true, then reuerence and honour me as a Godde, for the participacion of the dyuyne Nature whyche is in my mynde. But if the Soule doe dye toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wythe the bodye (as ſome aſſehea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Phyloſophers, flatterynge theym ſelues in theyr beſtyall lyuynge and wallowynge lyke Swyne in the fyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye puddle of theyr Epycuriall ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alyty haue affyrmed) yet you euer drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge the Goddes, beinge the Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, dyſpoſers, and gouernours of all the beautyfull ornamente and furny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of thys wydde woorlde ſhall not myſſe but Godlye and inuyolablye ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnyze
<pb facs="tcp:22986:69"/>and kepethe memorial of me. Theſe aduertiſementes and exhortaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Cyrus</hi> gaue to his ſonnes lyinge on his death bed. Now let vs (if you thinke good) take a ſuruay of our owne ſelues, and ſée wheather the ſame opynion and beléefe be not to bee founde in vs and in other of our countraimen. I wil be plain which thée, <hi>Scipio:</hi> no man in the worlde ſhall euer be able to perſwade me, that either thy father <hi>Paulus Aemilius,</hi> or thy two Graund fathers <hi>Paulus</hi> and <hi>Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or <hi>P. Scipio</hi> the brother of <hi>Aphrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> or <hi>C. Scipio</hi> his vncle, or many moe famous and worthye men, whiche here néede not to bee rehearſed, woulde euer haue attempted ſuch perillous aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res (onely to leaue a noble and worthye memoriall of their fame and valiaunce to their ſequele, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they wiſſhed ſhold take example of their fortitude, &amp; treade in the footeſteppes of their laudable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues wherby they myghte atchieue like ſucceſſe in their glorious affayres and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22986:69"/>not feare to dye in the quarrell of their countrie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foraine hoſtilitie inuadeth it) if with the quicke vnderſtandynge of their myndes they had not wel ſéene and conſidered that theyr poſteritye apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned and belonged to theym, Doe you thinke that I (for I may I truſte, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what vaunt and boaſt of my ſelfe as olde men are wont to doe) woulde euer haue vndertaken ſo many laboures and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full trauailes night and day, both in the time of peace and alſo of warre, if I had had this opinion fixed and rooted in my mynd, that my glorye and fame ſhoulde extend no further then my natural lyfe, and that when the one ceaſſed the other ſhould dye alſo? for if that were ſo, were it not (I pray you) a great deale better to leade a quiet life ſequeſtred and exempt from all hurlye burlie and toylinge bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and neuer to entermedle wythe contentious matters, and the laborious affaires of the weale publique? But the mynd of noble perſonages (I know not
<pb facs="tcp:22986:70"/>how it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth) erecting it ſelf &amp; taking courage, had euer ſuch a careful reſpecte to their ſucceſſion, as though when they wer departed out of this lyfe, they ſhold then at length &amp; neuer tyll then liue and flouriſh, their incomparable geſtes triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing ouer cancard obliuion &amp; their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous liues ouer mortal deathe. For if it wer not ſo, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules ſhold be immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, the mynd of euerye good &amp; vertuous man would not ſo earneſtly wyth al his ſtudy &amp; deuoireſeke to attaine and aſpire to immortal glory &amp; perpetual renowne Furthermore,<note place="margin">The god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly deſyre death but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlye ſeare it.</note> euery good and wiſe man dieth willingly, and reioyceth therin ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedingly, taking death to be a ioyful meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to ſomon him to endleſſe felicitie: on the other ſyde, euerye foolyſhe man dyeth vnwillinglie. Do you not thinke, that that minde whiche ſéeth better and further of, doth well perceiue and know that he goeth to a farre better ſtate then in this worlde is to be founde? Agayne, the mynd of the fooliſhe ſort whoſe ſight
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22986:70"/>is dimmer and duller doothe not ſée nor vnderſtand ſo much? But verily I haue a great deſire to ſee and beholde your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom I entyrelye loued and had for their ſinguler vertues in great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miracion. And not them onely am I ſoe earneſtlye affected to ſee, with whome I was verye familierly acquainted, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue both hard,<note place="margin">This place is tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge to two ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe printes.</note> read &amp; alſo write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am in my iorney to them (which I ſo greatly deſire) ther ſhold no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bring me back again, though he would &amp; alſo cold: neither to make me to retire to the place from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came, like to a bal, which Tenyſeplayers toſſe &amp; ſtrike to their counterplayers, &amp; they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> otherſide, yea though he would vndertade to runne my youth againe, as we read that <hi>Pelias</hi> was in his old age. I wil ſay more, if god wouldgrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me now in this age to retorne again to my infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and to be as yonge as a child that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth crying in his cradle I woulde refuſe &amp; forſake the offer with all my mighte:
<pb facs="tcp:22986:71"/>neyther would I when I haue alreadye in a manner runne the whole race and wonne the gole, be again reuoked from the ende markes, to the Liſtes or place where I toke my courſe at the firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out. For who would be contented, when he hath gotten the beſte game to bee forced to runne againe for the ſame? What pleaſure and commoditye hathe lyfe? yea rather, what paine, toile and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour hath it not? But let vs admit that it had great commodyty, yet vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it hath eyther an ende or els ſacietye. For I meane not to lament and deplore the lacke of the pleaſaunt and freſh time of my youthe, as diuerſe and the ſame right well learned men haue done, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe I repente, that I haue lyued, becauſe I haue ſo lyued and ledde my life, that I maye iudge of my ſelf, that I was not borne in vaine,<note place="margin">This life is but a Pylgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note> but rather for greate vtilitye and ſpecyall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. And I departe oute of this lyfe, as out of an Inne and not out of a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22986:71"/>houſe. For nature hath géeuen to vs a lodginge to remayne and ſeiourne in for a tyme, and not to dwell in conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. O lucky and bleſſed day, wherin I ſhall take my iourneye to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that bliſful troupe and conuocation of happye myndes, and leaue this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome world, being the vaile of al mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and the filthy ſinck of al myſchiefe. For I ſhal not onelye goe to thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men (of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſpake a litle before) but alſo to my deare ſonne <hi>Cato;</hi> whoe was a man of ſuche ſanctitie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as none more, of ſuch ſyncere &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayned honeſtye, as none better, whoſe bodye was wyth funerall rites putte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fyer and bourned to aſhes by me his father, whereas it hadde béene more méete and more agrée able to the courſe of nature, that my Bodye ſhoulde haue béene wythe ſemblable obſequeys and Ceremonyes fyrſte burnte and intumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late by him. But hys mynde and Soule not vtterlye forſakyng mée, but euer loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge
<pb facs="tcp:22986:72"/>and expectinge my commynge, is gone before into thoſe places of ioye, whither he perceyued that I my ſelf (ere. it be long) muſt alſo come. Which brunt of calamytie and heauie chaunce of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, I ſéemed paciently to ſuſtaine: not becauſe I did take the matter ſo pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in déede, but I comforted my ſelfe, thinking and déeminge that we ſhoulde not be long a ſundre, but after a time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to haue a ioyful méeting. Theſe are the cauſes and the very reaſons <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio,</hi> (becauſe you and <hi>Laelius</hi> ſayde you much meruayled therat) which make my old age to me eaſie and tolerable, and not only without al greuaunce and diſturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but alſo repleniſhed wythall expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente pleaſures. And if I doe erre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I thinke that the ſoules of menne bée immortall, verilye I am well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in the ſame erroure ſtyll to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, and as longe as I lyue, I wyll neuer renounce nor recante the ſame, wherein I take ſuche ſinguler pleaſure
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22986:72"/>and coumfort: and if it were ſoe, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deathe I ſhoulde féele nothinge nor haue no ſenſe at all, (as certaine Pety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggers and baſtarde Phyloſophers hold opinion) I feare not a whitte, leaſt theſe lippelabourers and Idioticall Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers whenne they theym ſelues bee deade, ſhoulde ſkoffe and make a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge ſtocke at this myne aſſertion and beléefe, becauſe they theym ſelues ſhall alſo bee wythout ſenſe and lyke to bruit beaſtes. But admitte, that after deathe wée ſhoulde not bée immortall, yet is it boothe conuenyente and alſo optable for a manne, whenne hée hath honeſtly played his parte in the pageaunt of this lyfe to dye and pay hys debte to Nature. For Nature as ſhee hath an ende of all other thynges, ſoe alſo of lyuinge. And olde age is as it weare the peroration or finall end of a mans time in this world, much like to the Epilogue or <hi>Cathaſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe</hi> of an Enterlude: the weariſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peticion or deſatigatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof we ought
<pb facs="tcp:22986:73"/>to auoyde and eſchewe, and eſpeciallye when we are fullye cloyed wythe ſacie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. Thus muche at youre requeſte I had to ſaye concernynge Olde age: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whyche, God graunte you maye arryue, that the thinges whiche you haue hearde of mée by mouthe, you maye proue true by certayne tryall and actual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:73"/>
            <head>A briefe abſtract of yeares.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought I might verye well in this place annexe this Catalogue or Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of ſuch Sages and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſonages as lyued long: aſwel for the ſimilitude and affinitye of the Argumente, as for the admiration and coumfortable readinge wyth pleaſure of the thinge it ſelfe: ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence in theſe oure dayes beinge in the laſte age of the worlde, not one amonge tenne thouſand lyueth the tenth part of their flouriſſhing time &amp; auncientie: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe peraduenture there bee ſome that wil ſay (whoſe wordes I can not denye haue ſome couloure of probabilitie) that the yeares in old tyme were not ſo long, as our yeares now a dayes are, and that euery Nacion reckened after their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes familier computacion. For whoſe ſatiſfaction, I wil ſhew the difference of diuerſe yeares, firſt of theſe ſundry yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res that yet are allowed, and then of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:22986:74"/>particuler yeares appropriate to ſundrye countraies and cities, and laſtly the authorities and minds of ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, concerning the compariſon of oure yeare and theirs together. Firſt it is to be conſidered, that there be iii. ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of yeares. One is named <hi>Annus Magnus, Annus Mundanus,</hi> or <hi>Annus Platonicus,</hi> contayning of our yeares (as not onlye <hi>Plato,</hi> but alſo <hi>Macrobius</hi> and <hi>Ioannes de ſacro Buſto</hi> do affirme) fiftene Thouſand yeres: in which time &amp; ſpace, the Sunne with all the other planetes &amp; fixed ſtarres of the firmament, retourne to the verye ſame poynctes and places, that they had at the firſt beginning. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> in the eyghte chapter of his fyrſte booke of Antiquities ſaieth it containeth but ſixe hundreth yeres. The ſeconde is called <hi>Annus Solaris,</hi> which is the ſpace wherin the Sunne completely finiſheth hys courſe throughe euerye ſigne of the Zodiacke, and retourneth againe to the ſame poincte whence it ſet out, which is
<pb facs="tcp:22986:74"/>in <hi>365.</hi> dayes, vi. houres and <hi>8.</hi> minutes of an houre. Theſe vi. houres collected &amp; ſet together do in foure yere amounte to xxiiii. houres, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpace of an natural daye. And this is the cauſe, why euery fourth yere (to kepe the yere at a certaine ſtaye) we haue leape yeare, and that yere, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarye hathe xxix. dayes and the yeare thre hundreth ſixtie and ſixe dayes. The odde eight minuts muſt be alſo diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loked vnto, for els in proceſſe and tract of tyme it will cauſe greate erroure and confuſion. For in <hi>120.</hi> yeares they do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a natural daye: Which beinge not obſerued, cauſeth the two <hi>Solſtitia,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Aeſtiuall</hi> and the Hyemal, that is to ſay in playner woordes, when the dayes are at the longeſt, and when they bee at the ſhorteſt, and alſo the two <hi>Aequinoctia,</hi> that is, when they daye and nighte are of one lengthe to goe one daye backe, whyche woulde in tyme, if it bee not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, make Chriſtmas (whiche is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readye gone frome his iuſte time at the
<pb facs="tcp:22986:75"/>begynnyng almoſt xv dayes) to be in the Spring, &amp; Midſomer to be in Autumne, and al the feaſtes and tymes of the yere to a prepoſterous order. The thirde is <hi>Annus Lunaris</hi> whiche contayneth the ſpace of a mouthe. Furthermore, <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> the firſt king of Rome, who liued ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hundreth and thirtye yeares before chriſt, of whom the citye of Rome was both buylded and named deuyſed a yere that contained but tenne monthes, wher of Marche was the firſt in honour of his father <hi>Mars,</hi> then Aprill, then May, then Iune, then <hi>Quintilis,</hi> ſo named of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that it had, becauſe it was the fyfte, thenne <hi>Sextilis</hi> becauſe it was the ſixte, which two names were afterward alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and called, the one Iulye and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Auguſte in honoure of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Octauius Auguſtus</hi> the firſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of Rome, then September, and ſo foorth to October-Nouember, and laſt of al December being the tenth. After the death of <hi>Romulus, Numa Pompilius</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded
<pb facs="tcp:22986:75"/>in the kingedome, whoo added Ianuarye and Februarye to make the yeare of xii. monthes, and after the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the <hi>Aegiptians,</hi> allotted to one monthe xxx. dayes, and to an other xxix, ſo that his yere had but thrée hundreth, fiftye, and foure dayes, whiche number agréeth not to the courſe of the Sunne. Laſte of all came <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> who eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the incouneniences, and erroures aforeſayde, added xi. dayes and ſixe hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſoe that thenne the yeare contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned three hundreth ſixty fiue dayes and ſixe houres, whiche yeare we euer ſince haue &amp; do obſerue. Thus the other ſhott at the marke, but thys <hi>Iulius</hi> by helpe of one <hi>Soſigenes,</hi> hytte the pricke wythein verye lytle, as before I noted. Some countrayes rekened the yeare by noone of theſe wayes, but vſed an other pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate maner. The <hi>Carians</hi> and the <hi>Acar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanians</hi> fyniſhed their yere in vi. months as <hi>Macrobius</hi> affyrmeth <hi>lib. 1 Saturnall.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:22986:76"/>The <hi>Arcadians</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſayth) made their yeare to be iii. monethes. The reſt of the Gréekes ended the yeare in <hi>354</hi> dayes. The <hi>Aegiptians</hi> as <hi>Solinus</hi> wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) had iiii. moneths to their yere, but the oldeſt and auncienteſt yere amonge them (as <hi>Cenſorinus</hi> ſayth) was but two moneths. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of theſe two famous wryters, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius</hi> and <hi>Herodotus</hi> affyrme, that the certaine order and ſtay of the yeare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes was amonge them onely. Some countrayes accompted the Sommer for one yeare, and the winter for an other.</p>
            <p>And as in yeres, ſo lykewiſe in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of dayes lyke diuerſitie is to be founde. For the <hi>Babilonians</hi> reckened a daye, the ſpace betwene the two Sunne riſinges. The <hi>Vmbrians</hi> from none tyll none. The <hi>Athenians</hi> betwene the two Sunne ſettings, Amonge the commune people a day is taken for the ſpace bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene morning and night. Some kynde of dayes are called naturall, and ſome
<pb facs="tcp:22986:76"/>Artificial. The natural daye is the ſpace of xxiiii. houres, reckening the night and the daye together. An Artificall daye is from the Sunne riſinge, till the Sunne going downe. The Clergie and Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes, the <hi>Aegiptians, Hipparchus</hi> the Philoſopher, apoinct a daye, from myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night to mydnighte. The Aſtronomers from none to noone. Nowe to aunſwere ſuch as can vneth béeleue that <hi>Mathuſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem</hi> and others liued ſo manye of ſuch yeares as nowe wee vſe, truth it is, that the yeres then, were neither of a monthe nor yet of thrée monthes longe, which, hereby we may manifeſtly perceyue, for as much as we reade that <hi>Solom</hi> hadde a Soune when hee was twelue yeares of age. Therefore it is credible, that either they were equall or els not muche leſſe then oure yeres are. Alſo we read in the firſte and fourthe Booke of <hi>Ioſephus de Antiquit. Iudaic,</hi> that the <hi>Hebrevves</hi> deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the yeare in <hi>Egipte</hi> before Noye his floud or the vniuerſal Catacliſme, which
<pb facs="tcp:22986:77"/>yere contayned. xii monthes, &amp; the ſame is alſo avouched by <hi>Polydor Virgilius,</hi> and <hi>Paulus Eberus</hi> late wryters. Thus haue I compendiouſly and briefely (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not preciſely collected theſe ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry computacions, whereunto I haue added for concluſion what the worthy <hi>Ioſephus</hi> wryteth concerning the ſame, wherin if anye thinge be through ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighte or otherwiſe by me myſconſtrued, I craue thy frendeſhyppe gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlye to amende it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22986:77"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The names and age of <hi>ſundrye long lyuers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Dam</hi> lyued ix hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth and thirtie yeres <hi>Eue</hi> as many. <hi>Seth</hi> ix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and twelue. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Seth</hi> ix hundreth and fiue. <hi>Kenam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Enos</hi> .ix. hundreth &amp; tenne. <hi>Malalehel</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Kenam</hi> eight hundreth, nintye and fiue. <hi>Iared</hi> the ſonne <hi>Malalehel</hi> ix. hundreth ſyxtye and two. <hi>Enoch</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iared</hi> thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth ſixtie and fiue. <hi>Mathuſalem</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Enoch,</hi> nyne hundreth ſixty and nyne. <hi>Lamech</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Mathuſalem</hi> ſeuen hundreth, ſeuenty and ſeuen. <hi>Noe</hi> ix hundreth &amp; fifty. <hi>Sem</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Noe</hi> ſixe hundreth. <hi>Arphaxat</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sem,</hi> foure hundreth thirtye and eyght. <hi>Salah</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of <hi>Arphaxat,</hi> foure hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth thirtye &amp; three. <hi>Heber</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Selath</hi> foure hundreth ſixty and foure, <hi>Peleg</hi> two
<pb facs="tcp:22986:78"/>hundreth thirtie &amp; nyne. <hi>Regu</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Peleg</hi> C Cxxxix. <hi>Serug</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Regu</hi> twoe hundreth and thirtye. <hi>Nahor</hi> the Sunne of <hi>Serug</hi> Cxiviii. <hi>Terah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nahor</hi> CCv. <hi>Haran Lothes</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther CCv. <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Abraham</hi> Clxxx. <hi>Iacob</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iſaac</hi> a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth fortye and ſeuen. <hi>Ioſeph Iacob</hi> hys ſonne Cx. <hi>Aaran</hi> the brother of <hi>Moyſes</hi> Cxxiii. <hi>Ioſua</hi> Cx. <hi>Heli</hi> the iudge, lxxxxviii <hi>Salomon</hi> lxxxxiiii. <hi>Iob</hi> Clxxxiii. <hi>Abraham</hi> Clxxv. Olde <hi>Tobias</hi> Cii. Younge <hi>Tobias</hi> lxxxxix. <hi>Sara Abrahams</hi> wife, Cxxvii. <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith</hi> Cv. <hi>Moyſes</hi> Cxx. Out of <hi>Plinie. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganthon</hi> King of the <hi>Tarteſsians</hi> Cl. <hi>Silli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> wryteth that he lyued CCC. yeares, as it appeareth in his third booke <hi>de bel.</hi> Po. <hi>Cyniras</hi> king of <hi>Cyprus</hi> Clx. <hi>Agimius</hi> CC. <hi>Epimenides Gnoſius</hi> Clvii, <hi>Pictoreus Aetolus</hi> CCC. kings of <hi>Arcadie</hi> CCC. <hi>Dando</hi> the Sclauonoies Dlxxxx. <hi>Impetris</hi> king of the Iſle <hi>Pulutine</hi> DCCC. Hys Sonne DC. <hi>Perpenna</hi> lxxxxviii. <hi>Marcus Valerius Coruinus</hi> C. <hi>Metellus</hi> byſhoppe
<pb facs="tcp:22986:78"/>C. <hi>Liuia Rutilius</hi> his wie lxxxxvii. <hi>Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> lxxxxix. <hi>Terentia Cicero</hi> his wife Cvii. <hi>Clodia Ophelus</hi> his wife Cxv. <hi>Luceia Mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma</hi> had a good vtteraunce and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the Stage C. yeares. <hi>Emolia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> lyued Ciiii. yeares. <hi>Sammulla</hi> Cx, <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanio</hi> aboue a hundreth. <hi>Hiero</hi> kinge of <hi>Sicilie</hi> lxxx. <hi>Maſiniſſa</hi> king of <hi>Numidia</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a hundreth. <hi>Gorgias Leontinus</hi> cvii. <hi>Xenophilus</hi> of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> Cv. <hi>Herodotus</hi> wryteth that the <hi>Aetheopians</hi> lyue aboue Cxxx yeares. <hi>Hippocrates</hi> the noble Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion borne in the Iſle <hi>Coa.</hi> Ciiii. <hi>Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> C. <hi>Orbilius</hi> of <hi>Beneuente</hi> C. <hi>Plato</hi> lxxxi. <hi>Sybilla</hi> of <hi>Cume</hi> a very longe age. <hi>Ouid</hi> wryteth <hi>lib 4. de Triſt,</hi> that his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyued lxxxx yeres. <hi>Narciſsus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> Cxvi. <hi>Neſtor</hi> ccc. <hi>Antonie</hi> Abbote .cv. <hi>Alexander</hi> biſhoppe of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>andria</hi> .lxxxxiiii. <hi>Alexander</hi> byſhoppe of <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinople</hi> lxxxxiiii. <hi>Agilus,</hi> Abbot C. <hi>Titus</hi> Sainct Paules diſciple Ci. <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus</hi> CCCix. Paule the firſt Heremite Cxiii. <hi>Paconius</hi> Abbot Cx. <hi>Proſdocimus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:22986:79"/>biſhop Cxiiii. <hi>Vandegiſillus</hi> countée Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine lxxxxii. <hi>Florentinus</hi> biſhop Cxxiiii. <hi>Guarinus</hi> biſhop of <hi>Bononie</hi> Cx. <hi>Viuentius</hi> Cxx, <hi>Homere</hi> the Poete Cviii. <hi>Hierome</hi> lxxxxviii. <hi>Helias</hi> Abbot Ci. <hi>Heroinꝰ</hi> ccciiii, <hi>Ioannes de temporibus</hi> CCClxi. <hi>Maurus</hi> Abbot lxxxxii. <hi>Maurilius</hi> biſhoppe lxxxx. <hi>Romualdus</hi> Heremite Cxx. <hi>Antonius Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor</hi> C. <hi>Syrus</hi> biſhoppe Cxxxii. <hi>Zaucles</hi> of <hi>Samothracia</hi> Ciiii. <hi>Pollio Romulus</hi> C. <hi>Saturnius Volucius</hi> Cxxxvi. <hi>Titus Fullo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> Clvii. <hi>Artoxerxes</hi> lxxxxiiii. <hi>Caelius</hi> writeth that one <hi>Maris</hi> liued Cxxiii. yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res whoſe bodye on the foreparte was like a man, and behind like a horſe. The people <hi>Hyperborei,</hi> whoe liue vnder the northe Pole called <hi>Polus Arcticus,</hi> haue alwayes holeſom winds, and know ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſickneſſe, nor vnquyetnes, wherfore <hi>Strabo</hi> wryteth that they liue a M. yeres. <hi>Galene</hi> liued Cxl yeres. <hi>Dorotheus</hi> biſhop of <hi>Antioche</hi> Cxix. <hi>Tiro</hi> the ſeruaunte of <hi>Tullius Cicero</hi> C. <hi>Theremon.</hi> Heremite c. <hi>Carneades</hi> the philoſopher C. <hi>Cirnae</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:22986:79"/>of <hi>Iudia</hi> Cxl. <hi>Marſilius Ficinus</hi> Cxvi. <hi>Terence</hi> of <hi>Bonomie</hi> C. <hi>L. Tertulia</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimyne</hi> Cxxxvii. <hi>Simon Cleophae</hi> biſhoppe of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> Cxx. <hi>Crouius Anachoreta</hi> Clv. <hi>Apolonius Thyaneus</hi> Clxxx. <hi>Seneca</hi> borne at <hi>Corduba</hi> in Spayne Cxiiii. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricius</hi> the ſecond biſhop of <hi>Niuerne</hi> Cxxii. <hi>Gartius Aretinus</hi> Ciiii. One <hi>Rycharde,</hi> in the time of <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> CCCC. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias Anochoreta</hi> Cxx. <hi>Hugh,</hi> who ſucceded S. Barnard Cxvii. Many others mighte here haue bene recited, verye not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rious and famous for their longeuitie, but I thought theſe few for this time and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to bée ſufficient.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Nevvton.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
